<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conscionable Christian: or, The indeuour of Saint Paul, to haue and discharge a good conscience alwayes towards God, and men laid open and applyed in three sermons. Preached before the honourable judges of the circuit, at their seuerall assises, holden in Chard and Taunton, for the county of Somerset. 1620. By Richard Carpenter, Doctor of Diuinity, and pastor of Sherwell in Deuon.</title>
            <author>Carpenter, Richard, 1575-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843372</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1061:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conscionable Christian: or, The indeuour of Saint Paul, to haue and discharge a good conscience alwayes towards God, and men laid open and applyed in three sermons. Preached before the honourable judges of the circuit, at their seuerall assises, holden in Chard and Taunton, for the county of Somerset. 1620. By Richard Carpenter, Doctor of Diuinity, and pastor of Sherwell in Deuon.</title>
                  <author>Carpenter, Richard, 1575-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 119, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By F[elix] K[ingston] for Iohn Bartlet, and are to be sold at the signe of the gilded Cup, in the Goldsmiths Rowe in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:1"/>
            <p>THE CONSCIONABLE CHRISTIAN: <hi>OR,</hi> THE INDEVOVR OF SAINT PAVL, TO HAVE AND DISCHARGE a good conſcience alwayes towards God, and men: laid open and applyed in three Sermons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached before the Honourable Judges</hi> of the Circuit, at their ſeuerall Aſſiſes, holden in CHARD and TAVNTON, <hi>for the County of Somerſet</hi> 1620.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD CARPENTER, Doctor of Diuinity, and Paſtor of <hi>Sherwell</hi> in <hi>Deuon.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Acts 23. 1.</bibl>
            <q>I haue in all good conſcience ſerued God vntill this day.</q>
            <bibl>2. Cor. 1. 12.</bibl>
            <q>This is our reioycing the teſtimony of our conſcience, &amp;c.</q>
            <bibl>Aug. cont. Petil.</bibl>
            <q>Conſcienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> malam laudant is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>nium non ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at Bona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mniantis conuitiam non vulnerat.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the gilded Cup, in the Goldſmiths Rowe in Cheapſide. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL HIGH SHERIFE OF SOMERSET, IOHN TREVELIAN of Nettlecom, Eſquire, &amp;c. The Authour wiſheth what <hi>the worke deſcribeth, the ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of a Conſcionable Chriſtian in this life, and in that to come, bleſſed immortality.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR: Your worth ſhineth in ſo high a Sphere of dignity, being now the worthily honoured high Sheriffe of the County; that if I ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to hold foorth a Candle to any, to behold the brightneſſe thereof, I might iuſtly bee cenſured of folly or flattery. But I haue no ſuch proiect: and in truth, it is not your annuall acquired greatneſſe, and eminency of office and place, but your continually inſpired goodneſſe, and life of grace appearing in your practice of piety, charity, and hoſpitality farre beyond many of your ranke and quality; which hath as it were by a ſecret forcible influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence drawne me vnto you; and this diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:8100:3"/> of a <hi>Conſcionable Chriſtian,</hi> from me. Which as it reſembles you much, ſo deſires to honour you long; &amp; ſo much the more to honor you, as you ſhall the more deſire and indeuor to reſemble it, and proceed in ſome competent proportion, to expreſſe and repreſent the lines, limbes &amp; linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof in the future courſe of your life and conuerſation. Wherof I conceiue no ſmall hope, hauing been an often eye-witneſſe of the manifold graces of God ſhining in you, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally inforced to take notice of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary integrity, in the faithfull diſcharge of your publike Magiſtracy heretofore; and at this time, in managing wiſely and worthily this important Office, whereunto your vertues haue aduanced you; from which (I doubt not) but you will come off commendably and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, without any gaſh or galling of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Which that you may the better doe, giue me leaue (whom you haue choſen at your ſeuerall Aſſiſes to be a Monitor to many) to bee alſo now a Remembrancer vnto you, that you put your ſoule to that noble imployment of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting vpon it ſelfe, and recollecting the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular knowne-paſſages of your well-neere ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt Magiſtracy, with an vndazeled and vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling eye, that ſo thorowly trying &amp; diſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what you haue done, and finding, vpon ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous examination of your wayes, words and workes, that as another <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> you haue wittingly and willingly done no man wrong, neither been voluntary Agent, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:8100:3"/> inſtrument in the doing of any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly; you may hereupon reſt aſſured, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured of this, that you haue carefully and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably accompliſhed your Office and duty: Whereof the Countrey makes thankfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and I cannot but heere to my knowledge giue publike teſtimony thereunto; being alſo deſirous, that the tender of this poore Paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent ſhould be, if it may be, a perpetuall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, how much I ſtand bound to you in generall, for your many Chriſtian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vouchſafed to mee in particular: I haue long (I confeſſe) run on the ſcore, ſo that the intereſt of your loue, exceeds the principall of my abilities: But yet, if verball payment may ſatisfie for reall benefits and goe for currant, I hope hereby at length to ſtrike out ſome part of my debt. At this preſent let it pleaſe you to accept this little monument of that great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which I deſeruedly beare vnto you: what propriety you iuſtly haue, both in the worke, and in the Author, it is well known to all which know vs. I need ſay no more but this, At your inſtance and intreaty theſe Sermons were prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; by your beſt deuotion they were atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and in teſtification of my dutifull loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, they are now publiſhed. You were the chiefe meanes and motiue to bring theſe meditations to the hearing of many; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cheerfully they runne to your hands, and are bold, vnder your name, to offer themſelues to the view of all.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:4"/>
            <p>And ſo humbly commending them to your gentle acceptation, and heartily committing you to the Almighties gracious protection, and to the Word of his grace, which is able to keep<note place="margin">Act. 20. 32.</note> you from falling, to build you further, and to giue you an inheritance with them that are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctified; I reſt euer preſt to be proued,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Sonne-in-law in all Chriſtian obſeruancy truly deuoted, RICH. CARPENTER.</signed> 
               <dateline>Loxford <date>the 20. of Septemb. 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8100:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader: In theſe later and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer times, wherein (as the Heathen of old complained) <hi>Malunt diſputare homines quàm viuere:</hi> Men delight rather to argue and diſcourſe of piety and Religion, then ſeriouſly to reduce the principles thereof into practice and action: It is much to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that we all feare God too little; and it may iuſtly be ſuſpected, that too many ſtand ſo affected in theſe dayes of long peace, as the Romans did in the time of their ciuill warres: Then ſome followed <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and they were weakeſt; ſome <hi>Pompey,</hi> and they were thought wiſeſt; ſome <hi>Craſſus,</hi> and they were accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worſt: So now ſome follow the fleſh, and are led by her corrupting allurements; ſome are Fauorites and Minions of the world, carried away with its glittering preferments; ſome are meere Factors for the diuell, fulfilling his crafty-cruell deſignements; all are ſet on worke, but vnder the Commander of this curſed <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate,</hi> for the moſt part ſo wickedly, that euery where there is a conſumption of grace, through the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of ſinne; piety complaining that ſhee is ſicke, charity neere dead, good workes buried, prayer and preaching neglected, honeſty and ſobriety derided, iuſtice and equity abandoned, truth and plaine-dealing
<pb facs="tcp:8100:5"/> impriſoned, faith and a good conſcience baniſhed and driuen out of the Countrey: For the recalling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of from baniſhment, or rather, for the inciting of Chriſtians to giue thereunto better entertainment, I had (I confeſſe) ſome extraordinary calling to thoſe places where theſe Sermons were preached, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more then ordinarily laboured, to worke by them powerfully on the conſciences of my Auditors, that they might be truly inlightened and inliued. To this purpoſe my deſire and ſtudy was (as the circumſtances of perſons, time, and place required) to lay the Axe of Gods Word cloſe to the root, and to apply my doctrine home to the heart, and ſo to ſet conſcience it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke.</p>
            <p>Now the whole and intire worke of conſcience (to giue by the way ſome light to the ignorant herein) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, as I conceiue it, in a practicall Syllogiſme: the maior and propoſition whereof ariſeth from the <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſis</hi> or treaſury of morall principles, and of ſacred rules wherewith the practicall vnderſtanding is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, for the ſauing direction of vs in all actions. The minor or aſſumption is properly Syneideſis-conſcience, that is, an actuall application of our knowledge, to this or that particular act or obiect; whence followes the immediate and neceſſary iſſue and office of conſcience; to teſtifie in reſpect of things ſimply done, or not done; in reſpect of things to be done, either to excite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, or to reſtraine and bridle; in reſpect of things done well, or wickedly, to excuſe and comfort, or accuſe and terrifie.</p>
            <p>As for example: thus it reaſoneth againſt lying; Euery lyar ſhall be baniſhed from the holy Mountaine
<pb facs="tcp:8100:5"/> of the Lord, and barred out of the new Ieruſalem, as the Syntereſis, from Pſal. 15. and Reu. 21. ſupplyeth the propoſition. But I haue thus and thus lyed for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, as the conſcience of the lyar telleth him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the aſſumption. Therefore I ſhall be baniſhed from the holy Mountaine of the Lord, &amp;c. A concluſion full of terrour. And as the liar is thus of his ſinne, and puniſhment due vnto the ſame, conuinced; So the vpright liuer, on the other ſide, may thus by conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences-reaſoning be comforted: Euery one that deſireth in heart, and indeuoureth in life, to walke vprightly before God and men, ſhall reſt in Gods holy Hill: But I, as the conſcience of the godly man telleth him, doe thus deſire and indeuour to walke vprightly: Therefore I ſhall reſt in Gods holy Hill. A concluſion full of life and conſolation. God grant vs ſuch conſciences as may inable vs to make ſuch concluſions. To this principall end, haue my poore indeuours, in this enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, been eſpecially directed; wherein, becauſe I know this age to be full of ſcience, penurious of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Gods ſchoole to be more of affection then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: therefore haue I the leſſe ſtudyed by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of choyce doctrines, to giue edge to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, accounting it more neceſſary to be inſtant in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and frequent in the vſe and application of ſome few pregnant poynts, for the whetting vp of the will and affection to holy duties, and warming of the heart with liuely deuotion in the practice of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Glad I would be, If I could but bring a pin or two, towards the decking of Chriſts Spouſe, whileſt others, out of their abundance, adorne her with coſtly Robes, and rich ornaments. Howſoeuer it be, I haue done my
<pb facs="tcp:8100:6"/> beſt, by the aſsiſtance of his grace, to the praiſe of his glory, and according to the nature of my Text, haue often and earneſtly preſſed vpon Chriſtians this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty of expreſsing in their conſcionable conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſauing power of inward ſanctimony, and the truth of a ſound conuerſion, aiming here and there, and euery where, generally at this, that the ſlumbring conſcience might be awaked, the erronious better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the tender confirmed, the ſad and heauie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and all, ſome way or other benefited. Which benefit of my vnworthy labours, if any any way haue obtained, let the goodneſſe of God be duly glorified and praiſed; and in their beſt vowes and prayers for the family of the faithfull, let me, his vnworthieſt ſeruant, be remembred. In hope hereof I reſt theirs, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus to be commanded, RICH. CARPENTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8100:6"/>
            <head>THE CONSCIONABLE CHRISTIAN.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Preached at Charde, March.</hi> 4.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text: Acts 24. 16.</bibl>
               <q>And heerein (or in this therefore) doe I indeuour my ſelfe to haue alwayes a cleare (or inoffenſiue) conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God and men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it be ſufficient to accuſe, who ſhall bee innocent? Not Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, though neuer ſo faithfull in his function, neuer ſo ſincere and vpright in his conuerſation. Wee finde him (as many times elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) ſo heere in this Chapter, called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, for his life and doctrine too, before <hi>Felix</hi> the Gouernour; and at once accuſed of both, and abuſed in both, by <hi>Tertullus</hi> a mercenary O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>our, who making b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>attery his Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8100:7"/> and bold lying his Logicke, beginning with the one, and concluding with the other; layeth to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> charge (no maruell then if zealous Miniſters taſte of the ſame cup in this laſt and worſt age) that hee was a peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, a moouer of ſedition, a maintainer of ſects, and a polluter of the Temple. To all which obiected crimes, or rather forged calumnies, the bleſſed Apoſtle, with great patience, and no leſſe confidence, pleadeth not guilty; &amp; hauing by pregnant reaſons &amp; powerful arguments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felled thoſe vniuſt imputations, with a victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous grace, proceedeth to the ingenious confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his faith, and courſe of life; and thus in effect ſaith: <q>As concerning my Religion; bee it knowne, that after the way which my aduerſaries call hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that only true God, with a true heart, in a true manner, not as man hath inuented, but as God himſelfe hath in his Word pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, beleeuing all things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law and the Prophets; eſpecially, holding faſt this aſſured hope and full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion (as the maine Baſis, and principall pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of my Profeſſion) that the reſurrection of the dead ſhall bee both of iuſt and vniuſt, and that we ſhall all appeare in that Day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 5. 10.</note> Tribunall of the Sonne of God, gloriouſly viſible, in the <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 21. 27.</note> forme of the Sonne of man, to render an account, and to receiue a reward according to our <note n="c" place="margin">Reu. 20. 12.</note> deeds. In due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8100:7"/> and ſerious conſideration whereof, I doe labour and indeuour my ſelfe to liue vnblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and to keepe alwayes a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and men: For ſo it followeth in my Text; which being by way of Paraphraſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what inlarged, offereth it ſelfe to your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter apprehenſion and vnderſtanding in theſe termes:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And heerein, or in this therefore</hi> (as reuerend<note place="margin">Paraph. Text.</note> 
               <hi>Beza,</hi> a long fixed ſtarre in the firmament of our Church expoundeth it) <hi>doe I Paul</hi> (the ſeruant of the Lord, and Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt) <hi>exerciſe my ſelfe,</hi> (earneſtly indeuour, ſtudy, and ſtriue, as a Runner to the goale, a Wreſtler for the game, a due Tasker and Day-labourer for the appointed wages and gaine) To haue, to keepe, and diſcharge (the Originall will beare it well) to haue <hi>alwayes</hi> (in all caſes, in all places, vpon all references and occurrences whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, through the whole tenor of my life) <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> (as Monitor of my duties, defects, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, blemiſhes, as moderatour of my deſires and affections, and vnder God, principall Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all my thoughts, ſpeeches, and actions) <q>Yea; Heereunto fully, freely, actually, punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, doe I bend and extend all my ſanctified will, wit, power, policy, and all, to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by all meanes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,<note place="margin">Note.</note> cleere, acquitting conſcience towards God and men, that is, a conſcience voyde of offence, not ſtaggering, tripping, or fayling any way for matter or manner, either in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8100:8"/> duties of holineſſe and piety towards God, or of righteouſneſſe, peace, or equity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men. <hi>And heerein, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> which words being thus expounded by way of diuiſion, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the duty of our conſideration,</p>
            <list>
               <label>Three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable points of obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The firſt, S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Chriſtian practice and actuall imployment, grounded on the hope of the reſurrection: <hi>Heerein therefore doe I exerciſe my ſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The ſecond, is the matter ſubiect of his<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> imployment and exerciſe; <hi>to haue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue an vpright conſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The third, is the latitude &amp; extent of the ſame, either
<list>
                           <item>In reſpect of time, <hi>to haue a good conſcience alwayes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>In reſpect of the obiects, <hi>to haue and diſcharge a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>God &amp; Men.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>THe bleſſed Apoſtle confeſſeth in the verſe<note place="margin">Illuſtr. Text.</note> foregoing my Text, that he confidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued the doctrine of the Reſurrection, and (therfore) in a well grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded expectation therof, profeſſeth himſelfe heere ſtudious of a godly life, and vnblameable conuerſation; Hee had well learned, that Chriſtianity conſiſted not in idle ſpeculation, but induſtrious negotiation; and therefore ſets to the worke, not doing it by a Deputy, or putting it ouer to after-times, but for the preſent, without doubt or delay exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe; <hi>Heerein I exerciſe my ſelfe.</hi> He vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood well enough, that the beſt duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8100:8"/> the greateſt diligence; and therefore <hi>vltimata voluntate,</hi> with all might and maine, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth himſelfe in this, to haue alwayes an vpright conſcience. Hee knew, that to make a ſhew of deuotion and piety towards God, and not to procure things honeſt in the ſight of men, ſauoured of hypocriſie; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to obſerue a kind of peaceable truth, and plauſible equity in our dealing with men, and to be regardleſſe of Religion and Zeale in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Gods worſhip, was no other then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane formality; and therefore with a ſettled reſolution, indeuoureth to hold a concurrence and correſpondencie of both in their order, that is, firſt, to approoue the truth and ſincerity of his ſeruice, in all duties Diuine towards God, and then with all diligence and dexterity, to performe all humane dues and duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</p>
            <p>Theſe (Right Honourable and Beloued) are the ſeuerall bounds and limits of my intended Meditations on this Text, anſwerable to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall limmes and lineaments of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> holy practice and profeſſion ſhaddowed forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for the more liuely deſcribing and portray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which in their proper colours and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, three generall doctrines and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">3. Doct. obſ.</note> are principally to bee obſerued; Whereof the firſt reſulteth, and iſſueth from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue; The ſecond, from the manner; The third, from the matter of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſe and imployment, as in order
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8100:9"/> they offer themſelues to bee handled.</p>
            <p>The firſt Doctrine, ariſing from the motiue<note place="margin">1. Doct.</note> (to wit) the hope Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of iuſt and vniuſt, is this: That the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope and ſettled expectancy of the day of Reſurrection and Iudgement to come, when we ſhall render account, and receiue a reward according to our deeds, is, and ought to bee a forcible allectiue to draw on Chriſtians to the earneſt purſuit of godlineſſe, and conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of true Religion. <hi>Tolle ſpem Reſurrectionis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. in 24. Mat.</note> (ſaith golden-mouthed <hi>Chryſoſtome) &amp; reſoluta eſt omnis obſeruantia pietatis:</hi> Take away the hope of the Reſurrection, and the building of piety wanteth her foundation. For vpon this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation all the Apoſtles haue builded their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to amendment of life and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 17. Now God admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth<note place="margin">Acts 17. 30. 1. Theſ. 4. 2. Tit. 11.</note> all men euery where to repent, becauſe he hath appointed a Day, in which he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe. And 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 3.</note> Wee know, when Chriſt Ieſus ſhall appeare, wee ſhall bee like him, and euery one that hath this hope, purgeth himſelfe, as he is pure. So S. <hi>Peter;</hi> Seeing the Heauens ſhall paſſe with a<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 11.</note> noiſe, the Elements melt with heate, and all theſe things be diſſolued; what manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> ought yee to bee in holy conuerſation and godlineſſe? Yea, ſeeing that ye looke for theſe things, be diligent, that ye may be found of him in peace, and blameleſſe in that Day. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of which Day, called the Day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration<note place="margin">Acts. 3. 21.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8100:9"/> of all things, hath euer beene, is, and will be to ſuch as feare God, a forcible prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to vertuous atchieuements and religious actions. Then, then indeed runs a man cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the Race of Chriſtianity, when hee knowes that he runs not at vncertainety: <hi>Tolle</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>viatori ſpem perueniendi, &amp; continuò franguntur vires ambulandi:</hi> He blunts the edge of induſtry, that denies recompence, and where there is no apprehenſion of a Day of remuneration, there is little care of proficiency, or ſtriuing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. For to reaſon as the Apoſtle doth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. How can we, dwelling on earth, deſire<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20, 21.</note> to haue our conuerſation in heauen, if we looke not for the ſecond comming of our Sauiour? and how can we looke for his comming, except we beleeue the Reſurrection? and how can we beleeue the Reſurrection, vnleſſe wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that power by which he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelfe? Againe, How doe wee acknowledge our God to bee Almighty in power, without the faith of the Reſurrection? and how can wee haue the faith of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, without the hope of a Sauiour? and how can we haue hope of a Sauiour, without an heauenly conuerſation? So that the life of this conuerſation is hope, by which wee expect the comming of a Sauiour: and the ground of this hope is faith, by which wee are aſſured, that at his comming hee will change our vile bodies, and make them like to his glorious Body; and the reaſon of this faith (beyond reaſon) is his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8100:10"/> power, by which hee is able to accompliſh all things after his good will and pleaſure. All theſe be linkes ſo diuinely hanging and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding each on other, in that golden chaine of the Apoſtle, that if we let ſlip one, we loſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable hold-faſt of all; but good Chriſtians miſſe not of any, but eſtabliſhed in faith, rooted in hope, and abounding in loue, ſet forward in an holy courſe of life, and follow hard towards<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 14.</note> the Marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt, knowing that they are begotten by the immortall ſeed of the Word, in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 3.</note> of the Church Militant on earth, to a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope of an inheritance immortall and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed in the Church Triumphant in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> This hope, as it giueth vs an edge, that wee ſhould earneſtly affect &amp; couet ſpirituall things, ſo doeth it giue vs a backe alſo to indure all things; for why doe the ſeruants of God beare croſſes and loſſes ſo patiently, abſtaine from euill ſo carefully, purſue the things that are good ſo cheerefully? but becauſe they looke for a glorious reſurrection, as the full end of all Gods promiſes, when the wicked ſhall haue their full puniſhment, and the godly their full payment; when the wicked ſhall (both in body and ſoule reunited) be made ſenſible of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of miſety, and intolerable wretchedneſſe in hell, and the godly which haue but breathings heere, ſhall bee bathed in a ſea of comforts, and inioy the conſummation of bliſſe and complete happineſſe in the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8100:10"/>
            <p>Doubtleſſe, this holy perſwaſion of a Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">Eſa. 26. 19. Hoſ. 6. 3. Ezek. 37. Dan. 7. &amp; 12.</note> to come in the Day of Reſurrection (by the Prophets and <note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor 5. 10. Rom. 14. 10. Reu. 20 12.</note> Apoſtles, and by our <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 5. 28. Mat. 25.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour himſelfe ſo liuely deſcribed) hath euer poſſeſſed the hearts of Gods Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and the life of this perſwaſion hath been the death of ſinne in them, and ought to bee in vs the remembrance, that there is <hi>dies &amp; Deus vltionis,</hi> a day and God of reuenge: for his power vnreſiſtable, for his wiſedome infallible, for his Iuſtice inflexible, ought to ſtrike ſinne in the blade, breake it in the head, and kill it to the heart; and the due Meditation of the reuniting of our bodies and ſoules in that day, to be ioynt partakers of heauenly felicity, ſhould mooue vs all, to conſecrate both the parts of the one, and faculties of the other, as pure Nazarites to the ſeruice of God, in all holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, and ſobriety.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Oh then that this Meditation might take due poſſeſſion, and make deepe impreſſion in your hearts that are Magiſtrates, in ours that are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in all of vs Chriſtians, that ſo in all our doings, dealings, preachings, pleadings, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and proceedings, making account of that Day of accounts, when wee ſhall bee called to account for them all, wee may hence-forward conſcionably retaine God and his Word for our Counſellor, and the true feare of God for our Sollicitor, and by the works of piety, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and charity, according to our ſeuerall places and callings, lay ſo good a foundation heere,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8100:11"/> that we may lay hold of euerlaſting life heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. For our better direction and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein, let vs looke ſeriouſly on thoſe worthy patternes of well-doing, <hi>Dauid, Paul, Iob,</hi> and other faithfull ſeruants of God, and withall take notice for our inſtruction and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thoſe praiſe-worthy things, which vpon the like conſideration of the Day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, they both did, and reſolued to doe. And to begin with the Princely Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Dauid. Pſal. 101.</note> moſt apparent it is in the 101. Pſalme, (which it ſeemes he made, when hee firſt drew the ſoueraigne breath of a King, to giue notice to the world what an excellent Gouernour he would be, and all others by his example ſhould be) that he voweth and proteſteth that hee will doe wiſely and worthily, both in the morall carriage of himſelfe, and in the domeſticall well ordering of his family, and in the politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call religious gouernement of his Kingdome and Countrey, vpon expectancy of the Lords comming: I will doe wiſely (ſaith he) in the<note place="margin">Verſ. 2, 3, 4.</note> perfect way, till thou commeſt to me, &amp;c. being well aſſured, that nothing is ſo ſure as his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, nothing ſo great as hee that ſhall come, nothing ſo ſtrict as the Iudgement to come; and therefore nothing ſo needfull as to liue godly, to walke warily in priuate, to worke wiſely in publike, vntill his comming.</p>
            <p>And to goe on with our zealous Apoſtle S.<note place="margin">2. Paul.</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> certaine it is, that he did not much paſſe by mans day, or eſteeme of mans doome, but in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8100:11"/> reſpect of the iudgement and approbation of God (with whom his worke and wages were) hee had an accurate vnceſſant care, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both to walke vprightly, Gal. 2. and to<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 14.</note> diuide the Word aright, 2. Tim. 2. and for the<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2 25.</note> euidencing of his great loue towards Chriſts little flocke, and him the great and good Shepherd thereof; hee ceaſed not to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh<note place="margin">Acts 20. 31.</note> euery one night and day with teares; he ceaſed not, <hi>ecce laborem,</hi> to admoniſh, <hi>ecce of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium,</hi> euery one, <hi>ecce amorem,</hi> night and day, <hi>ecce vigilantiam,</hi> with teares, <hi>ecce compaſsionem, &amp;c.</hi> Such a painfull, pitifull, powerfull diſpenſer of the Word was he: neither yet did his care con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt onely in fulfilling his miniſtery by fidelity of diſpenſation, in publiſhing all the counſell of God, in preaching conſtantly, plainly, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to the conuiction of the conſcience, the information of the vnderſtanding, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the will, whereunto all Miniſters ſhould aime; but alſo by integrity of conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and ſingular ſanctimony of life (which is the very ſoule and life of the Miniſtery) whereof, in the Acts of the Apoſtles, and many<note place="margin">Acts 22. 23, 24.</note> paſſages of his Epiſtles we haue abundant teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. Phil. 4 9.</note> He knew, the people would hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the truth of Religion in his mouth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they did ſee the power of it in his life; and therefore he did as well teach their eyes by his conſcionable doings, as their eares by his comfortable doctrine, making full reckoning, that one day he was to be called to a reckoning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8100:12"/> for both, in regard whereof he thus triumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concludeth, 2. Tim. 4. I haue fought a good<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 7.</note> fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, and kept the faith, rauiſhed with this heauenly hope and ſoule-ſolacing aſſurance that a Crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe was laid vp for him, which the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge would giue vnto him in that day. The expectation of which day of reckoning and recompence, as it made Saint <hi>Paul</hi> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and faithfull in fulfilling his Miniſtery: So did it make holy <hi>Iob</hi> very cautelous in the<note place="margin">3. Iob.</note> priuate courſe of his life, and moſt carefull in his publike gouernment and Magiſtarcy. As for the former, I made ſaith he, Cap. 32. a Couenant<note place="margin">Iob 31. 1.</note> with mine eyes, not to looke or thinke on a Maid, or any other thing, whether gift or bribe, pleaſing to the luſtfull eye. Why? this ſeemes too much preciſenes (will the carnall man ſay:) for lookes and thoughts are free. Oh, but what<note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> portion then ſhould I haue from aboue, ſaith <hi>Iob?</hi> q. d. I dare not giue way to my fleſh and the luſt thereof in any ſort: for this were to depriue my ſelfe of the comfort of the Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit heere, and of happineſſe heereafter: and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I ſhould heerein eſcape the cenſures of men, yet, Is not deſtruction (ſaith hee) to the<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> wicked? that is, Hath not the Lord meanes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiueable by man, for the puniſhment of the vngodly? and can he not bring ſecret ſinnes to open ſhame? yea grant that it be kept cloſe from the eyes of the world, yet doth not hee behold<note place="margin">Verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> my wayes, and tell all my ſteps? verſ. 4. though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8100:12"/> men take view onely of the outward action, yet God looketh vpon the inward diſpoſition and affection of the heart, and hee hath placed alſo his deputy-Intelligencer, conſcience, within mee, to teſtifie againſt me.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like ſpirituall reaſons and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments <hi>Iob</hi> vſed to keepe himſelfe in order, and to affright himſelfe from all manner of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in his priuate comportment.</p>
            <p>And as for his publike gouernment, you ſhall finde him liuely deſcribed and charactred in the 29. Chapter, to be the Oracle of Wiſedome,<note place="margin">Chap. 29.</note> the Guardian of Iuſtice, the Refuge of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, the Comet of the guilty, the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and defender of the fatherleſſe, poore and needy, the Patron of peace, and the perfect Myrrour and paterne for all Magiſtrates, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them in the wiſe managing of all publike affaires of Iudgement and Mercy: in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all which duties, <hi>Iob</hi> ſhewed himſelfe very ſedulous and ſollicitous; yea, moſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous he was of doing well, and moſt timorous of doing euill, becauſe he was aſſured, that God himſelfe would one day come to viſit all his doings; and then, <hi>Quid faciam,</hi> ſaith he, verſ. 14.<note place="margin">Chap. 31. 14.</note> What ſhall I doe, when God ſhall riſe vp to iudge me? when he ſhall viſit me, what ſhall I anſwere?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> If iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> but thinking of the Day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, come on with his <hi>Quid faciet?</hi> What ſhall he doe? Alas then, <hi>quid fiet?</hi> what ſhall be done to the vniuſt? whoſe bodies muſt boyle, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8100:13"/> ſoules fry for it, when God comes to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? If righteous <hi>Iob</hi> make queſtion what hee ſhall doe or ſay; Alas, what then ſhall the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous be able to ſay or doe for themſelues? What ſhall mercileſſe preiudicate bribe-taking Magiſtrates, mercenary illiterate ſoule-ſtaruing Miniſters, vſurarious extorting State-ſpoyling money-mongers, ſacrilegious Church-polling Patrons, and rent-racking Land-lords and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, couetous time-ſeruing Court-officers, and vnconſcionable Lawyers, with that conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious crue of brothel-hunters, Alehouſe-hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all other blaſphemous Sabbath-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruffians, reuellers, and ſcornefull mock-Preachers? What will theſe, or any of theſe be able to ſay or doe at that Day? <hi>Quando non</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>perorabit lingua, ſed denudabitur conſcientia,</hi> when the bookes of conſcience ſhall be opened, and the mouth of iniquity be ſtopped, and all vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and flagitious ſinners ſhall bee vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; when a feare and conſternation of mind ſhall ouertake the hypocrites and preſumptuous tranſgreſſors in Sion, and none of them ſhall be able to anſwere this fearfull queſtion, Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<note place="margin">Eſa. 33. 14, 15.</note> vs ſhall dwell with the deuouring fire, with the euerlaſtings burning? But thoſe which walke in iuſtice, and ſpeake righteous things, refuſing gaine of oppreſſion, ſhaking their hands from taking of gifts, ſtopping their eares from hearing of blood, and ſhutting their eyes from ſeeing euill, euen they ſhall dwell on high, and ſee the Lord in his glory. The time preſſing me
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8100:13"/> forward, I cannot ſtand now to preſſe this in particular to the preſent occaſion, onely my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, that all in generall, and you in ſpeciall, which are to act any part in this weekes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne buſineſſe, would often rub vp your memories, with that ſaying of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> Gen. 39.<note place="margin">Gen. 39. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I doe this, and ſo ſinne againſt God?</hi> and rowze vp your conſciences with this medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iob, What ſhall I doe then, when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to Iudgement?</hi> And that you may not then doe amiſſe, but be found of God in peace, bee exerciſed now as <hi>Iob</hi> was in doing well. Follow peace and holineſſe, without which, yee cannot<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> ſee God; put on, as hee did, iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a robe and Crowne; bee eyes to the blind, feet to the lame, fathers to the poore, to the widow and fatherleſſe. Shew your ſelues, in your ſeuerall imployments, men of courage,<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21. 2. Cor. 13. 8.</note> fearing God, dealing truly, and hating coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: iudge, pleade, witneſſe, work nothing againſt the truth, but all for the truth; vſe the Law lawfully, wrong not the right, right the wronged, iuſtifie the righteous, condemne the wicked, as the Lord commandeth, Deut. 25. To<note place="margin">Deut. 25. 1.</note> be briefe, let the view of theſe Aſſiſes ſuggeſt to your conſciences a <hi>memorandum</hi> of that vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall circuit and viſitation, which Chriſt, the Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the whole world, and Iudge of all Iudges, will in one day begin and end; and let the meditation of this Day, when we ſhall all ſtand to our triall, for life or death, ſerue as the dead hand on the nauell, to cure the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8100:14"/> dropſie of worldly and vnwarrantable deſires, and be as a continuall Monitor vnto vs all, ſo to number our dayes, and ſo to ſpend them, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, and euery night wee may be able to make vp a good account, eſpecially in the night of death, and in the morning of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the making vp of which account againſt that day, in the beſt manner, the due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſollicitous and induſtrious manner of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> exerciſe and imployment, will ſerue for more then an ordinary preſident and incouragement vnto vs all; and therefore, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the method propoſed, I will now deſcend from the motiue, to the manner, as it offereth it ſelfe here to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Heerein <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by an vſuall Elleipſis, for<note place="margin">Second part.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) I doe exerciſe my ſelfe; Hee ſaith not, Herein I haue laboured, but cannot now, or will labour, but may not yet; hee ſpeakes not doubtfully, Peraduenture I ſhall; or faintly, I purpoſe if I can; or fainedly, with ſome popiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reſeruation, I, or ſome other will; but cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, confidently, <hi>ſatis pro Apoſtolo,</hi> yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, inſtantly, <hi>ſatis pro imperio:</hi> In this doe I exerciſe my ſelfe, I deferre not the doing of it, knowing it moſt neceſſary to be done. In this I doe really and for the preſent, without delay, readily, exerciſe (not others) but my ſelfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, to haue a good conſcience, &amp;c. Whence (you ſee) many particular pregnant inſtructions might eaſily be deduced; but the general obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation naturally ariſing therfrom (vnder which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8100:14"/> the reſt are contained) and vpon which I meane onely to inſiſt, is this: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That heauen, and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, eſpecially the treaſure of a cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is an heauen vpon earth, is not eaſily come by, gotten and attained; but with diligent ſedulity, with a zealous care, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious conſtancy to be ſought for and acquired. It was not for nothing that the great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all things, Chriſt Ieſus, who can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand vs, might condemne vs, will certainly iudge vs, doth ſo often and ſo earneſtly incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that ſoule-ſauing counſell, <hi>Striue to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7. Luk. 13. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the ſtrait gate,</hi> into the narrow way which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto life; he knew, and would haue vs to know, that without ſtriuing and ſtruggling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our corruptions, without ſtooping, and ſtripping our ſelues of our carnall worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, there is no paſſage into the narrow portall of heauen. We muſt, as the holy Ghoſt chargeth, walke circumſpectly and preciſely, Epheſ. 5. Make ſtraight ſteps to our feet, Hebr.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 15. Heb. 12. 13. Pſal. 39. 1.</note> 12. Walke by a rule, Gal. 5. 16. Take heed to our wayes, with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 39. and ſtriue to keepe an euen and direct courſe, as it were by line or leuell, that ſo we may haue entrance into the ſtrait gate, into the which, the proud man, with his high lookes; the ambitious, with his aſpiring thoughts; the malicious, with his ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vncharitable heart; the Vſurer, with his full bags; the drunkard, with his full cups, and corrupt lungs; the adulterer, with his fulſome minions, and waſted loynes, can haue no admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8100:15"/> no admittance, if they liue, and lye and die in their ſinnes without repentance: <hi>facilis deſcenſus auerni;</hi> A man may goe to hell without a ſtaffe, as the Heathen ſaith; <hi>ſed reuocare gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp;c.</hi> But to make a ſtep to heauen, and ſo to ſeeke the Kingdome thereof, as to find it, ſo to finde it, as to inioy it, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus eſt, non puluinaris, ſed pulueris:</hi> This, this indeed is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of great worth, a worke requiring much heedfulneſſe, diligence, and watchfulneſſe. Whereof our Apoſtle had good experience, and therefore for our learning and imitation, he hath left it recorded, that hee did forget what<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 13, 14.</note> was behind, that is, account whatſoeuer he had done or ſuffered already for Gods ſake, to bee as nothing, not worth the naming; but this one thing he did, he did indeuour himſelfe to that which was before, and ſtriued to doe better, and to bee better, and followed hard towards the Marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Ieſus Chriſt; So heere in my Text hee exerciſed himſelfe, that is, with diligence and dexterity, and continuall indeuour to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; he purſued this one thing aboue all other things, to wit, the hauing and holding of a good conſcience, eſteeming it at ſo high a rate, as the Merchant did the Pearle for which hee ſold all<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 46.</note> that he had, accounting all things elſe as droſſe and loſſe in compariſon thereof. He knew, that the imperfect Eſſayes, proffers, and momentany purpoſes, and propenſities of lazie languiſhing wiſhers &amp; woulders, ripen not, reach not home
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8100:15"/> thereunto, and therefore with a ſteady ſettled will, and full reſolution with the greateſt bent and extent of his regenerate rectified affection, (ſuch as was in <hi>Dauid,</hi> where hee vowed and<note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 106.</note> ſwore that hee would keepe Gods righteous iudgements; and in <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> where hee reſolued<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24. 15.</note> that whatſoeuer others did, hee and his houſe would ſerue the Lord) purſueth the purchaſe of this heauenly Iewell, a good conſcience; in which purſuit he deſerueth our beſt imitation, and moſt zealous emulation too. So that as S. <hi>Ierom,</hi> hauing read the religious life and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable death of <hi>Hilarion,</hi> ſaid, Surely <hi>Hilarion</hi> ſhall be the Champion which I will follow. So hauing heard the godly care, and continuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had to keepe an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right conſcience; wee ſhould all, both Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Miniſters, and all other officers and inſtruments of Iuſtice here preſent, religiouſly reſolue to make Saint <hi>Paul</hi> our Champion and guide, in a buſineſſe of ſo ſingular conſequence, henceforward exerciſing our ſelues in this, to haue alwayes a good conſcience towards God and men; to haue, I ſay, that tranquillity of mind, that heauenly Muſicke, whereon the old Philoſophers doubtfully harped, but the good Chriſtian heart onely heareth it, and anſwereth it with iuſt meaſures of ioy: Which ſpirituall harmony (to giue you by the way a taſte of it, for the ſharpning of your appetite after it) as a ſong of three parts, conſiſteth in a three-fold<note place="margin">Pax ſuprà, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rà, intrà.</note> peace, with God aboue vs, and men without vs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8100:16"/> and the ſoule within vs; and therefore is both hard to be gotten, and rare to be found.</p>
            <p>But after wee haue ſought heauen and earth,<note place="margin">Note.</note> behold, where onely the wearied Doue, the humbled Chriſtian may finde this Oliue of peace, this peace of a good conſcience, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that reconciliation to God, in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and fruition of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, which the eternall Peace-maker, the<note place="margin">Eſa. 9.</note> Sauiour of men, and anointed of God, CHRIST IESVS, hath procured and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 19.</note> by the infinite price of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood; the benefit whereof hee offers to be apprehended of vs by the ſpirituall hand of faith: <q>Receiue then peace, and be happy; beleeue, and thou haſt receiued; by faith thou<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 16.</note> art intereſſed in all that either God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, or Chriſt performed. The faithfull apprehenſion and application of Chriſts all-ſufficient ſatisfaction, makes it to bee thine.</q> Vpon this ſatisfaction thou haſt the broad Seale of pardon and remiſſion; vpon remiſſion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes reconciliation; and vpon reconciliation, peace of conſcience. O heauenly peace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alone we are at league with our ſelues, and God with vs, without which, all other pleaſures are to be pitied; without which, the heart will deny to be cheered, though all the world bee her Minſtrell and Muſician. When therefore thy conſcience, like a ſterne Sergeant, ſhall catch thee by the throate, and arreſt thee vpon Gods debt, let this be thy plea, that thou haſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8100:16"/> already paid it, bring foorth that bloody ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance ſealed to thee from heauen vpon thy true faith, and ſtraightway thou ſhalt ſee her fierce lookes changed into friendly ſmiles, and that hand which was ready violently to drag thee to priſon, now louingly to imbrace thee, and fight for thee againſt all temptations and accuſations whatſoeuer. For what can accuſe or condemne, where God and the conſcience do acquit? <hi>Hic murus ahaeneus eſto, nil conſcire tibi:</hi> Let this be thy fortreſſe and brazen Bulwarke in all aſſaults of thy ſpirituall enemies, that thou haſt no ſinne vnrepented; no corruption vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed, with the guilt wherof thou canſt charge thy ſelfe. Surely thou canſt not be by the falſe<note place="margin">Saluianus.</note> iudgement of another made miſerable, who art thus by the true teſtimony of thine owne conſcience become bleſſed; the vniuſt excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the wicked without, ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hurt thee, whilſt the iuſt acclamation of thy witneſſe within, doth cleere and cheere thee; nay, rather thou ſhalt make to thy ſelfe a Garland of the falſe aſperſions of Sycophants, and be able comfortably &amp; confidently to ſay, as S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in a caſe not much vnlike ſaid; <hi>Fideliter in conſpectu Dei dico, &amp;c.</hi> I ſpeake it ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely<note place="margin">Aug. cont. lit. Petil. l. 3. c. 6.</note> in the ſight of God, that I am not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to any of thoſe actions wherewith my aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary chargeth me, ſince the time I was baptized in the name of Chriſt, and therefore haue no cauſe to be ſad, but to reioyce and exult. Goe to then, ye righteous, reioyce in the Lord, ſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8100:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> merrily, ye that are purged and pacified by faith in Chriſts Blood, to the mighty God of your ſaluation. Walke cheerefully on in the way of peace, thus chalked foorth vnto you: let no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty be a ſufficient excuſe to hinder you in the purſuite of this peace of conſcience, which of all other things is moſt precious, and yeelds ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and durableſt contentment; and that you may ſo haue it, that you may alſo hold it faſt, and be confirmed in the ſame, put in daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice theſe few rules. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in reſpect of God, labour and indeuour by all holy exerciſes of<note place="margin">Rules for the preſeruing of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> Prayer, of hearing the Word of God, by confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Meditation, to find the fruition of his ſweet preſence renewed in you. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in reſpect of your ſelues and your actions, you muſt reſolue by a ſecret vow paſſed betwixt God and the ſoule, to refraine from all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of dipleaſing his Maieſty, to performe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall obedience in all required duties, and to doe nothing doubtfully with intricate ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of mind. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And laſtly, in reſpect of your eſtate, it behooueth you wholly to roll your ſelues, and relie on the prouidence of the Higheſt, and to conſider whatſoeuer comes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that it commeth from a Diuine hand, whoſe Almighty power is guided by a moſt wiſe prouidence, and tempered with a fatherly loue, and ſo to be perſwaded, the eſtate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are, to be beſt of all for you, becauſe he willeth it, who foreſees and effects what is beſt for his. Theſe, as a threefold cord diuinely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8100:17"/> twiſted, are ſufficiently able to ſtrengthen in vs, and to confirme vnto vs the hold-faſt of a good quiet conſcience. To the which generall rules, theſe particular helpes are ſubordinate, which the conſcionable Chriſtian may, and muſt vſe for his ſurer footing, and better furtherance in the way to heauen.</p>
            <p>Firſt, his holy care muſt bee ſo to heare the<note place="margin">1. Helpe.</note> Word, as with a ſettled purpoſe to yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from the heart, to the forme of doctrine<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 17.</note> whereunto he is deliuered; not talking, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe in a dreame, of the Kingdome of God, and righteouſneſſe thereof; or walking, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe (with reſpect to their profit or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) in ſome good duties, as <hi>Herod</hi> did; but with an heart inlarged by grace, running in all the wayes of Gods Commandements, bleſſing<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.</note> God for the day-light of the Goſpell, and the opportunity offered thereby, of caſting off the workes of darkneſſe, and putting on the armour of light; imbracing at all times the ſound of the Word, not onely when it commeth in a ſtill and ſoft voyce (gently admoniſhing vs to auoyd the quagmires of voluptuouſneſſe, the thorny copſe of couetouſneſſe, and the ſtickle path of<note place="margin">Prou. 3. 17.</note> pride, and to walke preciſely in the pleaſant and proſperous wayes of wiſedome,) but alſo when as a Trumpet it ſoundeth the Alarm of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ſecure and impenitent ſinners, that ſo he may be kept in awe, and ſay with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, O Lord, I heard thy voyce and was afraid,<note place="margin">Hab. 3. 2. Pſal. 119. 120.</note> my fleſh trembleth for feare of thy iudgments.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8100:18"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, with the faithfull, Eſa. 26. he is ſo to wait for the Lord in the way of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Verſ. 8, 9.</note> with his ſoule deſiring him in the night, and with his ſpirit ſeeking him in the morning, that thereby he may not onely be terrified, but as the Prophet there ſpeaketh, learne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and behold the high hand of God, as well in protecting the vertuous, and compaſſing them about with a wall of braſſe for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,<note place="margin">Ezek. 5.</note> as in puniſhing the vicious, (which in the Land of vprightneſſe doe wickedly) for their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that his profeſſion and practice may be no way mimicall, and grounded only on oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and confined by limitation, but ſincere and intire, without dodging and reſeruation; he muſt bind himſelfe with <hi>Dauids</hi> vow, and make<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 106.</note> a couenant betwixt God and his ſoule, that hee will performe his righteous iudgements, and be as the Clocke in the houſe where hee liueth, in the company where he conuerſeth, awaking others to doe their duties; and to this end muſt daily edifie himſelfe in his moſt holy faith,<note place="margin">Iude, verſ. 20.</note> praying in the holy Ghoſt, that God, (who in his conuerſion rowzed him out of the ſleepe of ſinne) would, by the neuer-ceaſing influence of that grace which firſt awaked him, keepe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his heart awake, and not ſuffer him to ſleepe as others doe, and let ſlip opportunity of grace, but preſerue him watchfull and ſober,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 6.</note> that ſo continuing the ſpirituall motion of prayer, thankeſgiuing, meditation, and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8100:18"/> of his heart and life, he may be preſerued in his ſpirit, and not tranſgreſſe, Mal. 2. and<note place="margin">Mal. 2. 16.</note> more and more ſtrengthen in himſelfe the good things which elſe would bee ready to dye,<note place="margin">Reu. 3. 2.</note> Reuel. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, he muſt with all diligence auoyd that repletion of worldly deſires, and carnall delights, which our Sauiour ſhewes to bee an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall enemy to Chriſtian watchfulneſſe, and with the wiſe Steward, Luk. 16. muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent<note place="margin">Luk. 21. 34.</note> to ſit downe and write fifty for an hundred:<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> that is, to abridge himſelfe of many profits and pleaſures; yea, by ſeaſonable abſtinence, he is to bring his fleſh into ſubiection, and by perpetuall ſobriety, to fence the City of his ſoule, that by any rout or riot of voluptuouſneſſe, the walls thereof be not broken downe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, he is with the Iſraelites, Numb. 9. to keepe the watch of the Lord; and as they fixed<note place="margin">Numb. 9. 23.</note> their eyes on the pillar of a cloud by day, and of fire by night, that according thereto they might reſt or remooue; ſo the conſcionable Chriſtian is to marke and obſerue diligently Gods workes and dealings with others and himſelfe, and when hee calles to feaſting or mourning, is to haue his eyes opened, and his ſenſes awaked, to entertaine the Lords mercies or iudgements with ioy or ſorrow, as hee hath appoynted: Contrary to the diſpoſition of<note place="margin">Amos 6. 8.</note> thoſe retchleſſe rebellious perſons by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets<note place="margin">Ier 5. 3.</note> condemned, Amos 6. Ier. 5. Eſa. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, that hee may conſtantly ſtand on the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8100:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> guard of faith and a good conſcience, hee is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to meditate on, and daily to expect Chriſts comming to Iudgement; that whether<note place="margin">Luk. 12. 35.</note> he come at euening, or morning, or midnight, he may be ready with his Lampe burning, and loynes girded, to entertaine him: and finally, for the full and finall preſeruation of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from ruine, hee is in humble prayer to<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.</note> commend the keeping thereof to the neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleeping Keeper of Iſrael, that hee making his Watch-tower therein, it may bee preſerued through faith vnto eternall life. Beleeue mee then (Fathers and Brethren) the procuring, and preſeruing of this true Diamond, which flings beames of comfort vpon the ſoule of this true Rubie, which carryes in her face the colour of vertue, of this ſoueraigne cordiall of a good and quiet conſcience, requireth an excellent exerciſed man, well skild in the pure and pious trade of Chriſtianity, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Wherefore whileſt the Wizards of this world (like to that couetous Cardinall, which preferred his portion in Paris, before his part in Paradiſe) exerciſe themſelues wholly; and their greateſt wit, cunning and policy, to gaine and retaine good eſtates, good Farmes, good fields, good friends, good houſes, good horſes, good clothes, good euery thing elſe, but care not for this onely permanent and Paradiſaicall good of an vpright conſcience; let all of vs that would be accounted godly, wiſe, &amp; proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for a better world, make it our principall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8100:19"/> care and ſtudy to get this choyce Iewell of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable vertue and operation, and to ſet it in the beſt and chiefeſt roome of our holy and hearty affection, as a bleſſing of all bleſſings: ſufficient for preſent maintenance, Pſalm. 84. and future<note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 11.</note> inheritance, Luk. 12. 31. With which, that wee<note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> may be really poſſeſſed, and ſo royally bleſſed, it is generally required of vs all, (as in part it hath, and ſhal be more fully declared hereafter) that we be, according to our ſeuerall callings, much exerciſed in prayer, in thankeſgiuing, in hearing, reading, and meditating of the Word; much in patience, temperance, repentance, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Gods mercies and iudgements on our ſelues and others, muſt be daily conſidered; his Temple, on publike ſolemne aſſemblies, duely frequented; his Throne of grace in priuate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion often ſollicited; his diſtreſſed ſeruants pitied and relieued; eſpecially wee muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured to a daily diligent ſearch and examination of our ſoules by that ſcrutiny in <hi>Seneca, Anima</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>mea, quid feciſti hodie?</hi> O my ſoule, what haſt thou<note place="margin">Ier. 8. 6.</note> done to day? that ſo comming to a true ſight and ſorrow of our ſinnes and corruptions, wee may humbly confeſſe them, feruently craue pardon for them, and by faith in Chriſts blood, be aſſured of the forgiueneſſe of them, and ſo with peace of conſcience, and ioy of heart, walke on cheerfully in the religious race of godlineſſe and vertue, to the iourneys end of endleſſe felicity. Herein, and therein ought we to be exerciſed, if we would inioy the comfort
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8100:20"/> and credit of conſcionable Chriſtians. And as theſe generall duties of Chriſtianity are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be performed; ſo the particular offices whereunto we are called, for the propagation of Religion and piety, or the preſeruation of order, iuſtice and equity in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, are ſeriouſly to be attended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted. <hi>Hoc agite,</hi> in the ſacrifices of the heathen gods, was a precept much vſed and obſerued: how much more in the ſeruices of the God of heauen, eſpecially in that great buſineſſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Iudgement, whereunto, by God, the King and the Countrey, the moſt of you are now deſigned, ſhould the ſaid precept (<hi>Doe yee this,</hi> that is, intend and apply all the faculties of your mind to the doing of it) be kept inuiolable: and that not only of you, the chiefe agents and miniſters, but of all others the inſtruments and aſſiſtants of Iuſtice; whether witneſſes, who are faithfully to prooue the action; or counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, who are formally to plead the cauſe; or Iurators, who are vprightly to cenſure the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations? Theſe, and euery of theſe, for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of a good conſcience herein, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, according to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> practice, muſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe themſelues, and that ingeniouſly, without ſiniſter affection; and that inſtantly, as the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is giuen, without put-offs to after-times, or any tedious protraction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> So that to come to a ſecond vſe of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine propoſed (me thinkes) here come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in compaſſe of iuſt cenſure, diuers Chriſtians
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8100:20"/> (as they eſteeme themſelues) to be ſharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, for their ſecurity and groſſe ſtupidity, in ſlighting, neglecting and procraſtinating ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duties, who thinke and ſpeake much of doing, but leaue to doe the effect of their thinking; who mention and motion many things fit to be acted and done, for the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſorders, and matters amiſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and family at home, in the Church and Common-wealth abroad, but as weaklings and ſlacke-graces, ſet not their hands to the worke, thruſt not themſelues forth with <hi>Dauids</hi> reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101. tot.</note> Pſalm. 101. to the ſpeedy execution of the ſame. Farre be they from the Prophets and our Apoſtles ſpirit and reſolution; farre from the obedient diſpoſition which was in Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> who according to Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, forthwith circumciſed his family, Geneſ.<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> 17. put away the bond-woman and her ſonne,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.</note> Gen. 21. yea, readily and betimes went on his<note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> iourney, to ſacrifice his onely beloued Sonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 22. and not asking a reaſon for it, which he thought to be preſumption; or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any carnall reaſon againſt it, which hee knew to be rebellion, inſtantly did that hee was called vnto, and commanded to doe with all expedition. But alas, theſe, (and are not ſome of you, Fathers, many of you, Brethren, ſuch?) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in fauour to themſelues, or for feare of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſtand ſtill with the idlers in the market, and doe nothing; or hauing begun well, reuolt<note place="margin">Math. 20. 1. Tim. 4. 10. Iudg. 5.</note> with <hi>Demas,</hi> diſappoynt with <hi>Meroz,</hi> or follow a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8100:21"/> farre off, as <hi>Peter</hi> did Chriſt, and doe not put themſelues forward to the reforming of any courſe that is euill, or the furtherance of any cauſe that is good. Yea; whereas the places and callings of ſome require, that they ſhould, as State-Phyſicians, purge themſelues of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered humours, that they might the more effectually worke on the humorous diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratures of others, and that they ſhould bee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of peace and piety, and patternes of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and honeſty, that ſo they might the more boldly reproue, and ſoundly repreſſe the lewd and lawleſſe irregularities of the ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> wherwith theſe times ſwarme: They, on the contrary runne a race of the like exceſſe of riot with others, and as if it were no diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, but rather an ornament vnto them; ſweare by authority, oppreſſe and extort by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; drinke, that I may not ſay, drab it too, without controll, without feare, care or conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Such, and ſuch, with ſhame and griefe I ſpeak it, are more then a good many of our neuter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſiue Magiſtrates, ſcar-crow Conſtables, and meale-mouthed vnder-officers in Towne and Countrey, who reſembling Oſtritches, which<note place="margin">Plin.</note> haue great feathers, but no flight; or <hi>Iupiters</hi> Blocke caſt amongſt the Frogs, to bee the king, whom they feared at firſt for its greatneſſe, but deſpiſed at length for its ſtilneſſe, ſuffer many hainous and hidious enormities of whoredom, blaſphemy, drunkenneſſe, prophaning of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8100:21"/> Sabbath, and wilfull recuſancy to paſſe by them vncontrolled, and are loth (leſt they might bee accounted preciſe and pragmaticall) to exerciſe themſelues in this, to ſee theſe and the like abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes puniſhed or reformed. So that as <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut.</note> ſometimes complained, that by the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſlothfulneſſe, the power of their aduerſary, <hi>Philip,</hi> King of Macedon, was greatly augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſo may we that are Miniſters iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that by the remiſneſſe of the aforeſaid Magiſtrates and Officers, the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, in thoſe his vicious vicegerents is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly inlarged.</p>
            <p>And therefore we doe the more humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you, my Honourable Lords, according to the great meaſure of courage, wiſedome and grauity which God hath giuen you, that you would with an heroicall ſpirit, incounter the many-headed monſtrous Hydra of ſinfull abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in theſe exulcerate times, and by an <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean</hi> arme of publike iuſtice, by degrees cut off the farre-ſpreading branches of all State-ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, couenant-breaking, Church-robbing, ſoule-murthering iniquity, which beareth vp creſt and breſt too, againſt all the inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy. Some faults, I know, may be like Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min-ſeed, beaten out with the rod, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh, Eſa. 28. other more ſcandalous<note place="margin">Eſa. 28. 27.</note> offences, like fitches, muſt be driuen out with a flaile, but the cart-wheele it ſelfe muſt make a noyſe, that is, the ſeuereſt puniſhment muſt bee inflicted, where the parties peccant will not bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8100:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> reformed, eſpecially the incorrigible followers of drunken <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the profeſſed friends of Romiſh <hi>Balaam,</hi> without dallying or delay, muſt be confronted, curbed, confounded; wherein, if you (my Lords) ſhall duly exerciſe your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and (as chiefe ſubſtitutes vnder God and our King, for the redreſſing of inormities in this Circuit) approoue your fidelity and integrity, aſſure your ſelues, wee ſhall bee euer ready to bleſſe God for you, &amp; to pray that God would bleſſe you, that you may continue a bleſſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, in the conſcionable execution of your Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall function.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> For the better execution whereof, the voyce of more then a man, and lowder then a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, is here neceſſary, not ſo much to rowze vp your conſciences, as to quicken and inliue the conſciences of inferiour Miniſters, officers, and inſtruments of iuſtice, by their ioynt labours and vigilancy, by their diligent inquiſition, true information, &amp; godly reſolution, to be aſſiſtant vnto you, in that great worke which you haue to doe, for the preſeruing and promoting of godlineſſe, peace and honeſty, for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and puniſhing of irreligion and luxury, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe contention and popery in theſe quarters of the Land. For as the Clocke, though it bee of<note place="margin">Simile.</note> the beſt metall and making, will not ſtrike or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and truly, but much therein will be out of frame and faſhion, if the leſſer wheeles, as well as the greater, keepe not their due and regular motion: So in the curious Clockworke of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8100:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Iuſtice, there will bee many exorbitancies (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the chiefe agents and moouers therein bee neuer ſo ſound in their integrity) if the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agents and inſtruments of Iuſtice (as witneſſes, in prouing the action; Counſellers, in pleading and proſecuting the cauſe; Queſt-men, in ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and cenſuring the euidences and allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) doe not alſo take care and make conſcience of diſcharging their duties.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image, Dan. 2.<note place="margin">Dan. 2. 32.</note> though it had a golden head, yet fell to the ground, and was daſhed in pieces, becauſe it had feet of clay: Euen ſo, though the chiefe Magiſtrates, the reuerend Iudges, and ſome worthy Iuſticers, bee as golden heads in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of iudicature, and doe deſire and indeuour to diſcharge their bounden duty; yet we heare too often, that truth and equity falles to the ground, becauſe theſe golden heads haue dirty feet, couetous vndermining ſeruants, corrupt &amp; cheating vnder-officers, which ſet to ſale, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; honeſty. If theſe things be not ſo, what meaneth the bleating of Sheepe and lowing of Oxen in my eares? as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake to <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. Sa.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 14.</note> that is, What meane the mournfull complaints of many poore plaine Country men, &amp; wronged Widdowes, who comming from farre to the Aſſiſes and Seſſions, for Iuſtice, and redreſſe of iniuries, returne full often home againe, with much diſcomfort of heart, ſit downe in heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cry out with teares and wringing of hands? <q>Alas, what a thing is this? I had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8100:23"/> thought to haue found Iuſtice, to haue had ſome redreſſe of my wrongs, reliefe of my wants, remedy of my euils, and an end of my ſuite in Law; but I ſee, I feele, I finde, that there is little equity, conſcience, or honeſty; much diſſembling, double-dealing, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, the moſt things are ruled by fauour and affection, and greatneſſe will haue the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, my iourney is long, my expences great, my trauell painefull, my caſe helpeleſſe, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour fruitleſſe, ſorrow endleſſe, for I thinke my matter put off from time to time, Terme to Terme, will neuer be ended, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>O ye ſeates of Iudgement, be aſhamed of this, and ye thrones of Iuſtice, bluſh at this iniquity, and ye Fathers and Brethren, on whom depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the redreſſe of theſe enormities; Let the cry, I beſeech you, of the poore fatherleſſe and innocent, enter into your eares and hearts, and mooue you to exerciſe true iudgement, and to<note place="margin">Zech. 7. 9.</note> ſhew mercy to your poore diſtreſſed Brethren. Vp and be doing what you ought to doe, and the Lord will bee with you. Heerein exerciſe your ſelues, that euery day, and euery action of the day, may witneſſe your deſire and indeuour to keepe and diſcharge a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and men. O ſuffer not your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and profeſſion, your credit and reputation, godly courſes, good mens cauſes, and your owne conſciences to lie a bleeding, whileſt you, too indulgent ouer your ſelues, and regardleſſe of the weale-publicke, lie a ſleeping. Rather as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8100:23"/> ſentinels in a watch, keepe your ſelues euer wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and intent to that worke, office, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, whereunto, by occaſion of theſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Aſſiſes, you are called and aſſigned. And as for you which are called hither to bee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to teſtifie the truth in matters of right or wrong, life or death; hearken briefly to your watch-word, and apply it to your ſelues as your owne proper Motto; <hi>Dicatur veritas, rumpatur inuidia:</hi> Though enuy and greatneſſe ſwell, ſweat, fume, fret, and burſt in twaine; ſpeake ye the truth, and the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, without feare or fauour, for ſmall as great, ſtranger as Brother; and the God of Truth ſhall be with you, and you ſhall haue both the teſtimony of honeſty for your credit among men, and the teſtimony of a good conſcience, for your comfort before God.</p>
            <p>And as for you that are Iurors of the Grand or petty Queſt, preſumed by the Law to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen of note for wiſedome and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity; or Yeomen of good fame, for credit and honeſty; hearken you likewiſe to your watch-word, and take this vnto you for your <hi>Impreſa, Ruat coelum, fiat iuſtitia:</hi> Though the skie fall, and the mountaines fume, and the mighty rich ill ones frowne neuer ſo much; yet let right be done; Sift well and examine all proofes and euidences; take heed, offer no violence to your conſciences; but according to truth and equity let matters be indifferently ſcanned, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8100:24"/> ſo let your vnpartiall verdict bee boldly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            <p>And as for you that are Aduocates and Counſellers of Law, I pray (without any Church-pinching prohibition) giue me leaue, in the name of him who can command you, may condemne you, and will certainely iudge you, to giue you alſo your watch-word and Embleme, which ſhall be this, <hi>Pereat nummus, ſeruetur innocentia:</hi> Let vniuſt gaine of doubled trebled fees periſh in the pit of hell, and bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abandoned, and according to your Office of pleading your Clients cauſe formally, and proſecuting his affaires faithfully, as much as in you lieth, let innocency be preſerued, vſe your beſt indeuour that right may bee had with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate expence, vſe the Law lawfully, that it may prooue a ſpeciall and ſpeedy remedie of wrongs, and not an Engine or trap to inſnare the weake, as many complaine; what? though for your plaine and conſcionable dealing, you loſe your fees and profit in the place of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on earth, yet bee aſſured of this, your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency ſhall procure you a better reward at the Iudgement ſeate in heauen.</p>
            <p>And now for you the reuerend Sages and honourable Iudges of this Circuit; and for you alſo, the praiſe-worthy Iuſticers of this Shire: what remaineth to be done? but only this, that (out of your owne ingenuous diſpoſition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any preſcription of mine) you ſhould ioyne together (what in places of iudicature may not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8100:24"/> be put aſunder) all theſe Symbolicall ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and quarter them as ſo many Scutchions, with the Armes of your houſes and offices, in this order: <hi>Dicatur veritas,</hi> firſt: <hi>Fiat iuſtitia,</hi> next: and then in the third place, <hi>Seruetur inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia:</hi> whereunto, adde for a Creſt (to make vp the compleate coate of a gracious Magiſtrate) <hi>Dominetur conſcientia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus if looking vp to God, who is preſent and chiefe Preſident in your aſſemblies, you ſhall, in a reuerent feare of his Name, ſee that truth bee teſtified and deliuered, Iuſtice done and executed, innocency preſerued and protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and a good conſcience in all things kept and preſerued; then ſhall the mountaines and hilles bring vnto the people peace and proſperity; then ſhall Iuſtice, as the Sunne; Mercy, as the Moone; other vertues, as the Starres; ſhine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your ſeates of Gouernement, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of the wicked, and the comfort of the godly: Which God grant, by the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his grace, to the praiſe of his glory.</p>
            <closer>Amen. Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8100:25"/>
            <head>THE CONSCIONABLE CHRISTIAN:</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Preached at Taunton, Aug.</hi> 7. 1620.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text: Acts 24. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Heerein therefore doe I exerciſe my ſelfe, to haue alwayes an vpright conſcience towards God and men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Prophet <hi>Ionas</hi> brought the ſame meſſage to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuites at his ſecond ſending vnto them: ſo doe I bring (Right Honourable, &amp;c.) the ſame Text of Scripture, at this my ſecond calling before you, deſiring to end what the laſt Aſſiſes I began, and to adde a roofe to that foundation which then I laid, and to giue an account of ſuch particulars as remaine yet vndiſcuſſed, of that generall Bill of parcels, which then I exhibited to your Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>And hauing then (as you may remember) ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8100:25"/> generally (according to the modell of time allotted for me to ſpeake, and you to heare) of the reall religious practice, and the actuall Chriſtian imployment of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting withall ſuch doctrines and vſes as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and manner of his imployment did offer to our obſeruation; I come now by orderly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent to handle more eſpecially the matter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and meane buſineſſe of conſcience; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was thus ſeriouſly imployed and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And for my better proceeding therein, and your profiting thereby, will by Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and your continued patience, preſent to the eyes of your vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Conſcience it ſelfe, as in her nature,<note place="margin">Diuiſ. 3. parts.</note> properties, and offices; in her power, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Soueraignty ſhe is conſidered to be great.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, I will commend to your view and entertainement, an vpright conſcience, as in her cauſes and effects; in her priuiledges, of being the beſt Gardian, Counſellor, and Comforter, ſhee is found to bee ſingularly good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirdly, as her goodneſſe (according to the latitude thereof) extendeth it ſelfe, in reſpect of time, alwayes, thorow the whole courſe of mans life, to the performance of all good duties, concerning God and man. <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doe I exerciſe my ſelfe, to haue alwayes a good conſcience towards God and men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8100:26"/>
            <p>Of each of theſe in their order; and firſt, of<note place="margin">1. Part.</note> conſcience, according to its power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; whereof my purpoſe is not to make an exact Scholaſticall Diſcourſe, but to touch the tops of generall notions, and with <hi>Gideons</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Iudg. 7. to lap at the brinkes of thoſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wherein others haue deepely waded, and with <hi>Ionathan,</hi> 1. Sam. 14. to giue you a taſte on the tip of my rod, of that ſight-cleering hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweetneſſe which therefrom may be gathered. Wherefore paſſing by the nicities and curious ſpeculations of Schoole-men, whether conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be an Act or an Habit, a faculty Theoricall or Practicall, ſimple or mixt, and compounded of both, whether ſeated in the vnderſtanding, will, or memory, as the proper ſubiect thereof, &amp;c. and paſſing ouer with a light finger, and dry foot, the Rhetoricall Notifications and witty Illuſtrations thereof, drawne from its<note place="margin">Illuſtr. conſc.</note> offices, adiuncts, effects, when and where it is deciphered to be a mans beſt friend, <q>ſooneſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; or bittereſt foe, hardlieſt appeaſed; a bridle before ſinne, to preuent it; a ſcourge after ſinne; to puniſh it, <hi>domeſticus index, index, carnifex;</hi> in briefe, to be the ſoules Schoolemaſter, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor, and Domeſticall Preacher, mans tutelar God and protector, Gods Law-Booke, Leiger, Ambaſſadour, Spie, Intelligencer, and the trueſt Prognoſticatour in a mans boſome or breſt, foretelling what ſhall become of him hereafter,</q> &amp;c. As an abſtract of all the premiſſes, I will briefly and plainely commend to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8100:26"/> the nature and eſſence of conſcience, vnder theſe termes of a definition or deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Conſcience (ſo called, either <hi>à cordis ſcientia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſcription of conſcience. <hi>Bern Aquin.</hi>
               </note> in reference to the ſoule, reflecting and recoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon it ſelfe, or <hi>à ſcientia cum alio;</hi> in reſpect to God, with whom it is a co-witneſſe of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is in man) is a noble and diuine power<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> and faculty, planted of God in the ſubſtance of mans ſoule, working vpon it ſelfe by reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Eſa. 30. 21.</note> and taking exact notice, as a Scribe or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and determining as Gods Viceroy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, Iudge of all that is in the mind, will, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, actions, and whole life of man.</p>
            <p>I name it a faculty, and not a bare act, becauſe<note place="margin">Prob. deſc.</note> ſundry actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as to teſtifie, accuſe, excuſe, acquit, condemn, are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it. I terme it a noble di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power, and not an humane acquired habit, becauſe acts and habits too may be got and loſt, depoſed from their ſubiect, and ſeparated from the ſoule; but Conſcience, as it is borne with vs, ſo it will neuer leaue vs; it is indiuiduall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, there is no putting of it to flight, or flying from it, <hi>nec fugere, nec fugare eam poteris:</hi> but it will ſay to thee, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> I will<note place="margin">Ruth 1.</note> goe with thee whereſoeuer thou goeſt. To bee briefe, I giue it roome and place in the whole ſoule, and doe not, as ſome haue done, thruſt it into a corner thereof, as if it were a part onely of the practicall vnderſtanding, becauſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of it cannot bee circumſcribed in nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower bounds then the ſoule it ſelfe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8100:27"/> the Hebrewes aptly call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Prou. 15. 15.<note place="margin">Prou. 15. 15.</note> and the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, heart or ſoule,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 20.</note> 1. Ioh. 3. Laſtly, I giue it the title of Gods Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter and deputy-Iudge, becauſe it is onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to God, and vnder him holds court in the ſoule of man, and is the principall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and chiefe controller of all his doings and deſires, determining of all his actions, either with him to excuſe and abſolue, or againſt him to accuſe and condemne; and that for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of ſome, and confuſion of others.</p>
            <p>The conſcience endowed with theſe royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">The vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis of conſcience.</note> reſideth, I confeſſe, principally in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, as her Metropolis Palace-Throne, and thereby exerciſeth her chiefe functions, but yet in the whole ſoule, commonly called the conſiſtory of conſcience, ſhe keepeth a compleat court, and in the ſeuerall parts thereof produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth occaſionally ſeuerall operations; whence, in common ſpeech we ſay, My conſcience tels me, I did this, or did not that; ther's an action of the memory. My conſcience bids mee, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids me to doe this; ther's an action of the will. And againe, It ſmites me, checks me, it comforts or torments me. What are theſe but acts of the affections recoyling vpon the ſoule? And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that whenſoeuer conſcience reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it ſelfe, and maketh a practicall Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, concerning the doing of that which is lawfull, and auoyding of that which is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; it hath ſome helpe from all the faculties both Theorick and Practicke, as (when that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8100:27"/> part of conſcience which the Ancients call <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſis,</hi> becauſe as a treaſury of rules and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it keepes the grounds of the Law naturall, and the principles of truth and equity) ſhall make thus the propoſition: <hi>All adulterers and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syll. Conſ.</note> 
               <hi>oppreſſours are worthy of fearfull puniſhment;</hi> and hereupon that other part, called <hi>Syneideſis,</hi> as an eye-witneſſe and remembrancer of all thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſhall make thus the aſſumption; But thou haſt committed adultery and oppreſſion, and ſhall conuince thee thereof, by all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of perſons, time and place: (whereupon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes an ineuitable concluſion.) In all this illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue diſcourſe, who ſees not a mutuall depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency on the mind, will and memory, which moues me to affirme Conſcience to be a diuine power compounded of them all? Whereat <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> aimed, when he tearmed it, <hi>Naturale iudicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium:</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> glanced, when he calles it, <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen. in 2. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>animae ſociatus:</hi> and the Philoſophers, when they ſpeake of a mans <hi>bonus genius:</hi> but he<note place="margin">Greg.</note> ſpake beſt, that cald it a booke, <hi>ad quem emendan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum omnes ſcripti ſunt libri,</hi> for whoſe ſake all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bookes are written: all other are but gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vpon this Text. And curſed bee that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary which corrupts the Text of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> To all here preſent, both learned and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, I muſt commend this Text, this book: whatſoeuer thou art which ſeekeſt for counſel, to know what thou maiſt doe by law: conſult with this booke of conſcience firſt, and ſee what it ſaith; it is an excellent booke, euen
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8100:28"/> in thine owne boſome, written by the finger of God, in ſuch plaine Characters, and ſo legible, that though thou knoweſt not a letter in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke, yet thou maiſt reade this; nay, thou canſt not for thy life but reade it, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it too, and yeeld to the truth and equity thereof, when it pleaſeth God to turne thy eyes vpon it. Open this booke then, and ſee what is written in this Law, how readeſt thou?<note place="margin">Luk. 10. 26.</note> Ponder vpon it, conferre with it; it is thy chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt and faithfulleſt counſellour at home, thou needeſt not be at coſt to ſeeke aduice abroad; it is ſtored with ſingular precepts and principles concerning the knowledge and practice of good and euill, perſwading to the one, diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the other. Hearken then vnto it, reade it in time for thy direction, leſt thou bee forced to looke vpon it too late, to thy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: it may be, the light thereof, by thy natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall blindneſſe, is much obſcured, and that the text letters thereof, by affected ignorance and wilfull malice, are more blurred, and euen blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out. Oh then, compare it with Gods Booke, and labour, by the helpe of Gods Miniſters, to haue it reformed and rectified. Happy is that man that hath a liuing, feeling, and waking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; for this ſhall keepe him ſo, that he ſhall either not commit ſinne, or not continue long therein, but the crying voyce of his conſcience will rowze him out of the bed of ſecurity, as the crowing Cocke did <hi>Peter,</hi> and bring him to<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> repentance; and bleſſed is that repentance and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8100:28"/> obedience which is wrought by the power and command of a rectified conſcience.</p>
            <p>And thus hauing made a ſhort ſurueigh of the nature of conſcience, as it is great, and Gods lieutenant in the ſoule of man, working more forcibly on all the parts and powers thereof, then all other agents whatſoeuer, ſitting in the vnderſtanding as Iudge, to preſcribe, prohibit, abſolue and condemne <hi>de iure;</hi> in the memory, as Recorder and witneſſe teſtifying <hi>de facto;</hi> in the will and affections, as rewarder and puniſher, <hi>pro iure aut iniuria facti:</hi> I will now, with the like breuity and perſpicuity, ſpeake ſomewhat of each of theſe offices diſtinctly: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And firſt, of conſcience, as it writes downe and keepes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord all our doings: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as it paſſeth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of them, with vs, or againſt vs: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, as it executeth the ſentence determinate.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſcience, as a Scribe or Notary, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">1. Office. Hieroglyphic.</note> in the cloſet of mans heart, with pen in hand, records and keepes a Catalogue, or Diary of all our doings, of the time when, place where, the manner how they were performed, and that ſo cleere and euident, that goe where we will, doe what wee can, the characters of them cannot be cancelled or razed. She omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no default through ſlowneſſe of hand, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrikes ſhee out any debt through deceit, like the vniuſt Steward, that bade put downe<note place="margin">Luk. 16. 6.</note> fifty for an hundred; ſhe cannot bee corrupted to conceale our faults, or ſmothered by tract of time, not to check vs for them, as appeared in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8100:29"/> 
               <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, whoſe conſciences troubled<note place="margin">Gen. 42. 21.</note> them in Egypt, for that cruelty which many yeeres before they had ſhewed towards their Brother in Canaan. It is good therefore for vs to agree with conſcience in time, and in all our wayes to ſeeke her approbation. And as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Martyr B. <hi>Latimer</hi> tooke ſpeciall care to<note place="margin">Fox Mart.</note> the placing of his words in his examination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bonner,</hi> when he heard the pen walking in the chimney behind the cloth, and deſcribing whatſoeuer he ſaid: So ought we circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to looke to all our doings and ſayings, and to guard, watch and ward our ſenſes (which are<note place="margin">Aug.</note> the gates and cinque-ports of corruption and luſts) ſith that conſcience is not onely the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuper-viſor, but the continuall recorder of all the actions of our life. Wee may caſt off our garments, but not our conſcience; wee may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten change place and ſeparate our ſelues from men, but when we are moſt ſolitary, then ſhall we finde conſcience moſt familiar with vs, and alwayes vpon our ſecrets: <hi>Falli poteſt fama, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>nunquam:</hi> her approofes or reproofes will neuer be wanting vnto vs. If we doe well, ſhee will ſpeake for vs and iuſtifie vs; if euill, without ſpeedy repentance, ſhe will bee as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſpeake againſt vs, and to accuſe vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Let no man therefore ſinne, in hope to lye hid for want of euidence againſt him, or lacke of witneſſes; for he carries a thouſand witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in his boſome, euen his owne conſcience,<note place="margin">Conſcientia mille teſtes.</note> which will ſurely teſtifie, when the Lord cites
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8100:29"/> it to anſwere, euen of the moſt ſecret ſinnes, and<note place="margin">Iob 24. 13, 14.</note> ſo teſtifie, that it will alſo terrifie in ſuch ſort, that all the men and creatures in the world ſhall not be able to comfort; whereof wee ſee an example in <hi>Adam,</hi> who immediately after he<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> had tranſgreſſed, ran away and hid himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the buſhes, though no man purſued him, no Angell reproued him, the Lord was not yet come vnto him, yet his conſcience for the fact accuſing him, all the pleaſures of Paradiſe could not auaile to quiet him, or doe him any good: and the like wee may note in <hi>Balthazar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> who though he had about him all the worldly comforts which the heart of man could deſire, yet becauſe the conſcience of his ſacrilegious villany was againſt him, nothing could remedy his griefe, or mitigate the terrour of the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing which hee ſaw on the wall; but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with extremely affrighted, he forthwith miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably expired. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let no man therefore (I ſay) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to commit any wickedneſſe, in hope to hide it for want of a witneſſe, ſith that conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſet in euery one of vs as a Regiſter, to giue teſtimony of all our actions; with the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting teſtimony whereof, as in doing euill, wee ought to be iuſtly terrified; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> So alſo with the comfortable teſtimony of the ſame wee ought, in well-doing, to bee ſufficiently chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and incouraged. Wee need not hunt after eye-witneſſes of our good workes; conſcience alone giueth ſufficient teſtimony and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; let vs be zealous and abundant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8100:30"/> in them, and ſeeke to pleaſe and praiſe God by them, and then with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Let the witneſſe<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 4. 2. Cor. 1. 12.</note> of our owne conſcience aboue all, comfort and content vs, in the middeſt of all ſlanders and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable ſurmiſes which malicious men ſhall haue againſt vs. To conclude this poynt, let vs in all our intents and actions, ſtudies and conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as conſcionable Chriſtians, looke vnto the Lord as the ſearcher of our hearts, and the tryer and rewarder of our workes, not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging our ſelues, whatſoeuer men thinke or ſpeake of vs and our doings, ſo God and our conſcience doe approoue them; nor content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues with mens approbations &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, when the teſtimony of Gods Word and our conſcience is not for them and vs. To which purpoſe, I remember, * hee ſpake<note place="margin">Secretary Cecill.</note> well, who in his dayes was accounted a worthy ſpeaker, and in reply to ſome that vniuſtly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligned him, ſpake thus praiſe-worthily: <hi>I will reſt henceforward in peace in the houſe of mine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and if I doe any good deeds, it is no matter who know them; if bad, knowing them my ſelfe, it is no matter from whom I hide them, they will bee recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before that Iudge from whoſe preſence I cannot flee: if all the world applaud me, and hee accuſe me, their praiſe is in vaine.</hi> Fame may help vs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience wil not; it is an infallible witnes; if ſpeaking for vs, it cheereth more then any cordiall; if againſt vs, it gnaweth &amp; tormenteth more then a corroſiue.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſcience, as Gods Deputy<note place="margin">2. Office.</note> Iudge, Oyer and Determiner of all cauſes and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8100:30"/> caſes in the Conſiſtory of the ſoule, paſſeth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, either of approbation or condemnation. on all our ſpeeches and actions, and that with ſuch authority, that by all the power and policy of the world, it cannot bee reuoked or reſiſted. Strong is the reaſoning of conſcience, when it conuinceth Pagans by the light of nature, but much more powerfull, when it conuinceth Chriſtians by the Word of God. Wherfore, as good S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets the ſentence of his conſcience,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 3. 2. Cor. 1. 12.</note> which did iuſtifie him againſt the calumnies of al men whatſoeuer that did cenſure &amp; condemn him, &amp; therin reioyceth and triumpheth in the midſt of tribulation; ſo the wicked and vngodly ſit down confounded at the Iudgement of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience condemning them, and therewith are ſtricken dead, at it were, in the midſt of their greateſt iollity and exaltation, as before, by the examples of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> hath in<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> part beene ſhewed, and in the tragicall ends of <hi>Saul, Achitophel, Haman, Herod, Iudas,</hi> and the<note place="margin">Eſth. 7.</note> like, might more fully and fearefully be exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified: but I haſten, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, conſcience, as inferiour<note place="margin">3. Offic.</note> onely to God, and chiefe commander, control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and executioner vnder him, euen in this life executeth the ſentence determinate of good or euill, rendring ioy vnſpeakeable to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and obedient, but ſhame and ſorrow, and terrour intolerable to the wicked and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. The truth of the former is cleerely eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced, in the holy conuerſation of life, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8100:31"/> happy expiration in death, of theſe faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, <hi>Iacob, Ioſeph, Iob, Ioſias, Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 50. 2. Chr. 34. 2. King. 20. 1. Sam. 12. 3. Luk. 2. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel,</hi> and good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> with others, of whom the ſacred Scriptures make honourable mention, as of ſuch in whom righteouſneſſe and peace met ſo together, mercy and truth ſo kiſſed each other, that the remembrance of their well led life, and the conſcience of their godly deſire and indeuour to walke inoffenſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in holineſſe and loue, exceedingly ſolaced them, and ſingularly ſupported them all their dayes, making them confidently and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to run on their Race, with an holy kind of contempt, beating backe the ſurges of all worldly wrongs and ſorrowes; <hi>Illiſos fluctus ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes vt vaſta refundit:</hi> As a brazen wall doth darts, or a mighty Rocke the billowes of the Sea. Thus conſcience, on the godly, executeth the ſentence of vnſpeakeable comfort in this life, and maketh death it ſelfe welcome to them, ſo that <hi>tanquam conuiuae ſatures mortis ſomno cedunt,</hi> like full fed gheſts, they goe willingly to their reſt in the bed of the graue: of whom, as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Mors ſine formidine expectatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>cum dulcedine exoptatur, cum deuotione excipitur.</hi> But as for the vngodly and wicked, a perpetuall <hi>non ſic</hi> is threatned vnto them by their owne conſcience, and on them this ruthfull irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence is paſſed; <hi>Non eſt pax impijs:</hi> There<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 21.</note> is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God: no true peace, either in life or death. <hi>Lateri haeret laethalis arundo:</hi> The griping, gnawing, and neuer
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8100:31"/> dying Worme of an accuſing conſcience euery where tormenteth them, and executeth the ſentence of remedileſſe condemnation vpon them, ſo that being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelfe-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 11.</note> through the guilt of their ſinnes, as <hi>Cain, Iudas, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Felix</hi> were: and as credible Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories<note place="margin">Acts 24.</note> declare; <hi>Beſſus,</hi> for ſecret killing of his father; <hi>Baſsianus,</hi> of his brother; <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> of his mother; and <hi>Richard</hi> the third, of his nephewes to haue beene: they leade heere a life euer-dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and feele as it were a death neuer-ending, which is no other but a fore-runner of that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and finall doome, which God (who will iuſtifie the ſentence and execution of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) ſhall, in that great Day of Iudgement, paſſe peremptorily on all the wilfully-diſobedient tranſgreſſors of his Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Take we heed then, that wee neglect not the checks of conſcience, when wee are bent vnto ſinne, nor deſpiſe the iudgement of conſcience, when we haue ſinned, but make haſte by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in faith, to be reconciled to God and it: for otherwiſe God will ratifie the ſentence of conſcience at the laſt Day, on all impenitent ſinners; and albeit now many ſuch by their wealth and hearts eaſe are rockt aſleepe, by ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, merry tales, eating, drinking, and gaming, are caſt into a ſpirit of ſlumber, yea, although the vnruly perturbations of their worldly luſts and affections be now ſo lowd, that the voyce of their conſcience, condemning their wicked wayes and workes, cannot bee heard; yet the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8100:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> Day ſhall come, and it will be a dreadfull Day for them, when theſe worldly negotiations ſhall ceaſe, and all fleſhly perturbations ſhall be ſilent, and conſcience ſhall be ſo ſhrill, that they ſhall both heare it, and be thryld at it, and gnaſh<note place="margin">Reuel. 16. 11.</note> with their teeth, and gnaw their tongues for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, to ſee how God taketh part with it againſt them: O what horrour and confuſion ſhall then couer the faces of ſuch as by a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of carnall pleaſures and worldly cares and affaires, drowne, and cry downe the voyce of conſcience, by which their euill wayes and workes are condemned, as the Drums and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brets<note place="margin">2. King. 23. 10.</note> in the ſacrifices of Molech did the cry of the infants which in Tophet were burned. But on the other ſide, O what honour and exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall crowne the heads of thoſe which heare and obey the voyce of conſcience, by the light of Gods Word rightly informed, which lend their eares, whileſt this good <hi>Caſſandra</hi> ſpends her tongue, and by her, in all their actions are willingly guided and directed! And ſo much (if not too much) may ſuffice to haue beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken generally of conſcience it ſelfe, as in her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, properties, and offices; in her power, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Soueraignty, ſhe is conſidered to bee great.</p>
            <p>Now, by Gods aſſiſtance, vnder the conduct<note place="margin">2. Part.</note> of his feare and your fauour, I will proceed, to commend to your view and entertainement, eſpecially, an vpright conſcience, as in her cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and effects, her proiects and priuiledges,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8100:32"/> ſhe is found to bee ſingularly good; and that<note place="margin">1. Bernard. Bona conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; turbata. 2. Bona conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilla.</note> not as ſhe is in continuall conflict with the fleſh, rebelling againſt the Spirit, and ſo afflicted with the ſanctified dolours of the new birth, but as it is after regeneration quieted with the ſence of remiſſion of ſinnes, and reconciliation to God in Chriſt, and ſo excuſing, cleering, chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and comforting the ſoule of the ſound Chriſtian. In reſpect whereof, ſome call it, The Paradiſe of the ſoule; The Iubile of the heart, <hi>Laetitia cordis, quaſi latitia,</hi> A ſurpaſſing inward ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, ſo dilating and inlarging the heart for ſome good in poſſeſſion, more in expectation, that the ioy thereof cannot well bee ſuppreſſed or expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And hence in a common popular apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is ſaid to bee a ioyfull remembrance of a well led life, ioyned with an hopefull expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a comfortable death and glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in reſpect of the mindes tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 7.</note> inioyed thereby, termeth it a peace which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, like to the hidden Manna and white ſtone, wherein a name was written, which no man knoweth but hee that inioyeth it, Reuel. 2. 17. <hi>Salomon,</hi> that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Reu. 2. 17.</note> Preacher, pointing at the peereleſſe pleaſure and immutable comfort of a good conſcience, compares it to a continuall feaſt, farre excelling<note place="margin">Pro. 15. 15. Miſhteh tamid.</note> the royall feaſt of <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> which laſted but nine-skore dayes: for this feaſt of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (whereat the Angels are Cookes and Butlers, and the bleſſed Trinity gladſome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8100:33"/> gheſts (as <hi>Luther</hi> boldly ſpeakes) without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion<note place="margin">Luth. in Gal.</note> of ſolace, or interruption of ſociety, is a continuall feaſt; A feaſt in life and health, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing the ſoule with dainty cates of diuine comforts; A feaſt in ſickneſſe, when world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings hopes hang downe their heads like a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, and lag like a Ruffians ſtarcht Ruffe in a ſtorme of raine; yea, in death a feaſt, when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is worth a world, and all worldly comforts and comforters forſake vs, yea, in the Day of Reſurrection, and after that Day (when all theſe ſhaddowes ſhall flie away) a feaſt for euermore. No maruell then that Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> being rapt and rauiſhed heerewith, breaketh foorth into the ſingular commendation of the admirable endowments thereof, ſaying, <hi>Bona conſcientia eſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in form. hon. vit.</note> 
               <hi>titulus religionis, templum Salomonis, ager Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, hortus deliciarum, gaudium Angelorum, &amp;c.</hi> A good conſcience is the Title and Crowne of Religion, the Temple of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the field of Benediction, the Garden of delight, the ioy of Angels, and Sanctuary of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. But becauſe theſe, &amp; the like alluſiue notions of a good conſcience, frequent in the Fathers, are <hi>magis ſloridae quàm ſolidae,</hi> more pregnant for wit, then profitable for preſent vſe, I will ſay to them, as <hi>Iehu</hi> to the meſſenger of <hi>Iehoram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 9. 18.</note> 2. King. 9. Turne behind me; and will take hold of that more ſound deſcription thereof by <hi>Iſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi> affirming that a cleere or inoffenſiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ſuch a one, <hi>Quae nec de praeterito iuſtè ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſiod. in 2. l. ſoli. loq.</note> 
               <hi>nec de praeſenti iniuſtè delectatur, nec de fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8100:33"/> ſollicitè perturbatur;</hi> that is, which is neither iuſtly accuſed for things paſt, nor vnlawfully delighted with things preſent, nor anxiouſly troubled for things to come.</p>
            <p>This clearing chearing conſcience, and that<note place="margin">Note.</note> perfectly good, <hi>Adam</hi> only had in his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whileſt in Paradiſe hee walked with God, without ſinne, and without feare in the ſtate of innocency: But now there is no way to come to it, to attaine and haue a quiet conſcience, and that but imperfectly good after regeneration, but onely by the mediation and reconciliation of Chriſt. Being iuſtified by faith in the Blood<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> of Chriſt (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) wee haue peace with God, Rom. 5. And againe, The Blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 9. 14.</note> once offred by his eternall Spirit without fault, purgeth our conſciences from dead workes, Heb. 9. Yea, ſo purifieth and pacifieth them, that it leaues no remorſe of ſin accuſing or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning in them. Nothing elſe in this world hath this vertue, ſaue Chriſts Blood alone; there is no pacification of the ſoule, without remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 1. Heb. 9. 22. Heb. 10.</note> of ſinne; no remiſſion of ſin without blood, no blood expiatory for ſinne, but Chriſts; no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this expiation, but by faith. The conſequence then is vndenyable: therefore by faith in Chriſts Blood, ſhed for the remiſſion of ſinne, we attaine peace of conſcience. No per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of the Sanctuary or charmes of Oratory can relieue it, no ſtraines of Muſicke or Songs of Angels can reioyce it. All other merriments and outward refreſhments whatſoeuer, haue no
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8100:34"/> more power to cure and quiet it, then popiſh holy-water hath to coniure the diuell. This, this is the honour, royalty, and peculiar dignity of Chriſts blood, by the hand of faith applyed to the ſoule for the full remiſſion of ſinnes. This alone can pacifie and make good the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and fully effect it; whereas otherwiſe all the glittering appearances of happineſſe, which dazle the eyes of doting worldlings, cannot bring it to paſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſuperſtitious Papiſt, troubled in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for ſinne, runnes vp and downe for reliefe, like an Hart with an Arrow in his ſide: <hi>Se rotat in vulnus tranſſixam circuit haſtam:</hi> hee ſends to the god of <hi>Ekron</hi> for helpe, hee buyes a pardon,<note place="margin">2. King. 1. 2.</note> goes to ſhrift, laſheth and launceth himſelfe, as the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> did, poſteth to a Maſſe, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<note place="margin">1. King. 18.</note> on in pilgrimage to a woodden worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten Lady, or painted Image, and all this while as an aguiſh man that drinkes water, his diſeaſe increaſeth; no ſhift of place, or change of aire can relieue him, being dogged and attended on by the helliſh hag of his conſcience; <hi>Quae ſurdo verbere caedit,</hi> which whips him in ſecret, and in ſilence telles him, <hi>Omnibus vmbra locis adero, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis improbe poenas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The prophane worldling likewiſe being vexed and perplexed in mind with the horrour of his offenſiue life, and the blood-hound of his guilty conſcience hunting dry-foot on the ſent<note place="margin">Prou. 28. 1.</note> of his former ſinnes, proiecteth fearfull things, <hi>ambulat in circuitu,</hi> walkes in a reſtleſſe round
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8100:34"/> or maze, like a ſea-ſicke wretch, from the ſhip to the boat, and ſo backe againe; and (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> paſſionately deſcribes it) runnes like<note place="margin">Aug. in 45. Pſa.</note> a Male-content, <hi>ab agro, in vrbem, &amp;c.</hi> from the field, into the City; out of the City, into his houſe; from the common roomes thereof, to his! bed-chamber; from thence, to his ſtudy or cloſet; and then out againe, to ſeeke for a merry companion, to ſee if hee can play away his trouble, and remooue the melancholy qualme, as carnall men account it, from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make; he eates profuſely, drinkes profoundly, ſports profanely, and all to lull the conſcience aſleepe, and to drowne her accuſing voyce by<note place="margin">2. King. 23. 10.</note> the clamours of needleſſe imployments. But all in vain, he doth but looſe his chaine, that it may be tyed ſtraighter; and ſmother the fire for a time, which will afterwards breake forth with greater violence; a ſeeming truce he may haue, true peace he cannot haue: for, <hi>Nocte diéque ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um geſtat in pectore teſtem:</hi> yea, <hi>peſtem,</hi> hee carries night and day his bane in his boſome, and of all earthly refreſhments may truly ſay, as <hi>Iob</hi> of his<note place="margin">Iob 16. 2.</note> friends, <hi>Miſerable comforters are ye all.</hi> But as for the godly Chriſtian, who is willing to illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and regulate his conſcience by Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Word, and the diuine Oracles of eternall truth, when ſcruples and troubles of conſcience doe ariſe, whereby hee is ſomewhat diſtracted or diſtreſſed; leauing all humane concluſions vntryed, vntruſted; he forthwith goes to God in prayer for direction, powres forth his ſoule
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8100:35"/> in ſupplication to him, imbraceth all good meanes of inſtruction and edification, layes faſt hold, by a liuely faith, on Chriſt Ieſus for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; and ſo finding Chriſt the great Phyſician of ſoules, or rather being found of him, findes, with all peace and tranquillity, his doubts reſolued, his griefe remoued, his feare cancelled, his heart confirmed in well-doing, his ſoule (as it were) rauiſhed with the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of his precious oyntments; ſo that <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas licet hic &amp; ille iaculetur polus, &amp; fractus illaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur orbis, impauidum ferient ruinae:</hi> though the heauens and earth crack and fly off the hinges, and the Mountaines be remoued, yet therewith he cannot be appalled; to him, being in Chriſt, and feeling it to be ſo, there is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or remurmuration of conſcience for ſinne; and therefore with glory to God in <hi>excelſis,</hi> he ſings <hi>De profundis,</hi> a <hi>requiem</hi> to his ſoule.</p>
            <p>You ſee then by that which hath been ſaid, how that the conſcience, which Gods Word (actuated by the Spirit) inlighteneth and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth, and the blood of Chriſt Ieſus, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the hand of faith, purgeth and pacifyeth, is the onely good conſcience. Know alſo, that truly to beleeue well, according to the tenour of Gods ſacred Word, and to indeuour duly to liue well in a cheerfull obedience to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, is both mother and nurſe of the ſame. <hi>It is the pure inmoſt blood which breeds, and the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call moyſture which feeds the bright Lampe of the ſoule, a good conſcience.</hi> Whereof for a concluſion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8100:35"/> to the premiſes, and an induction to that which followes this plaine and pregnant definition, proued by direct paſſages of Scriptures, offers it ſelfe to your Chriſtian obſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>A good or vpright</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 15. 15.</note> 
               <hi>conſcience is a diuine</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>power, and principall part of Gods Image in man, whereby he doth moſt reſemble the ſelfe-ſufficiency of God, which being</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>inlightened by Gods Word, and purged by</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 5. 1. Heb. 9. 14.</note> 
               <hi>faith in Chriſts blood, from the guilt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, and from dead workes, to ſerue the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Lord, ſpeaketh</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>peace with Gods allowance, is a</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iob 33.</note> 
               <hi>meſſenger of good things betwixt God and vs, and cheereth vp the heart with</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ioy vnſpeakable and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Definition, you may eaſily perceiue, how that knowledge and faith, repentance and obedience, peace and ioy haue their concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to make vp the precious odoriferous balme, or oyntment of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, knowledge and faith is requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, leſt it ſhould be blind and erronious.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, repentance and conſtant obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, leſt it ſhould be ſecure and licentious.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, peace and ioy, leſt it ſhould bee ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, galling, and needleſly tender and timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>To touch the tops of theſe perſwaſions, firſt,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 1. Knowledge.</note> it is by too lamentable experience well known, that for want of knowledge in Gods Booke, and of faith in the Goſpell (offering forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes onely by Chriſts blood) many ſottiſh ſoules liue in ignorance and darkneſſe,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8100:36"/> and in the very ſhadow of death, not able to diſcerne, by reaſon of their blind nature, and naturall blindneſſe, the things which concerne their peace; but thinking all religions will ſaue, or a good meaning ſerue the turne, or a <hi>Lord haue mercy</hi> at laſt caſt be ſufficient: Alas, many a Fly doe theſe ſwallow, many a ſinne vnſeene, vnſorrowed for, doe they digeſt, and in many things do they erre; as Chriſt told the Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Mark. 12. becauſe they know not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Mark. 12. 24.</note> and the power of God: The ignorance whereof, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> noteth, is the mother of<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 3. Coloſſ.</note> all miſchiefe; and therfore he earneſtly exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all ſecular perſons to get them Bibles, the phyſicke of their ſoules, to labour to bee more<note place="margin">Iob 22. 21.</note> acquainted with God in his Word, that they may grow vp therby in grace, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 13.</note> of our Sauiour Chriſt; without which ſauing knowledge, and faith grounded thereon, which the Hebrewes by an excellency call <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel Mekodeſh,</hi> ſanctifying wiſedome, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">2. Faith.</note> cannot be vpright. It is ſufficient vnto ſin to doe againſt conſcience, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in Rom.<note place="margin">Rom. 14. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </note> 14. ſheweth; whereunto that of Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> agreeth, <hi>Quicquid ſit contra conſcientiam, aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat ad Gehennam.</hi> But it is not ſufficient to duty and obedience, to doe according to conſcience, except it bee inlightened and rectified by the Word, without which information and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, conſcience often reſolues, where it ſhould reſtraine; acquits, where it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, and ſo erreth and offendeth diuers waies.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:8100:36"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by an erronious acceptation and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the lawes, faſhions and traditions of men, for the precepts of God; which is the errour of ſuperſtition, incident to ignorant, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant Papiſts, who make the Popes Dictates their practicall principles, and ſeeing (if they ſee at al) thorow the falſe ſpectacles of their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind guides, ſhew their obedience in thoſe things (to wit, in the adoration of Images, inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, meritorious obſeruation of dayes, and meates, and celebration of Pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Maſſes, &amp;c.) for which they can ſhew no commandement. All whoſe Religion in theſe and the like poynts of Purgatory, of prayer for the dead, of ſatisfactory ſeruices and ſacrifices of their owne inuention, may eaſily be ſwept away with the Prophets beſome, Eſa.<note place="margin">Eſa. 1. 12.</note> 1. <hi>Who required theſe things at your hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by a vaine aſſumption of falſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and a miſpriſion of good for euill, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill for good; and this is the errour of prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, frequent amongſt our common people, who inlarge their conſciences to the vttermoſt bounds of any pleaſure or profit, and vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of not being booke-learned, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their conſciences to prooue good Lawyers in Gods Booke, but liue in darke corners vnder blind Sir <hi>Iohns,</hi> and ſo take <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> Chalke for Cheeſe, riches for righteouſneſſe, policy for piety, who accounting gaine godlineſſe, and maintaining bad opinions to iuſtifie baſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doe hereupon, in the errour of their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8100:37"/> practiſe commonly ſwearing, propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sabbath, Vſury, Lying, Lottery, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemaine, without any regret of conſcience at all.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by falſe application of good prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as when from thoſe approued grounds and true propoſitions, (<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Religious adoration is not to be giuen to creatures:</hi> and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> likewiſe, Chriſtians haue liberty in things indifferent) theſe vnwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable concluſions are deduced; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Therefore we may not kneele in the Act of receiuing the Communion; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Therefore we are not bound to obey the Magiſtrate in things indifferent. Which errour of conſcience, I may call the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of too much ſingularity and preciſeneſſe, arguing their indiſcretion, who in their ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening curioſity will bee ouer-pleaſing God with better deuices then his owne, and take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to teach the Spirit to ſpeake according to the conſonants of the Alphabet, ſo long, till their wit turne to madnes, and end in miſchiefe, as appeareth by the courſe and condition of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts, Anabaptiſts, and Arminians at this day.</p>
            <p>For the auoyding of all which errours of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, prophaneneſſe and preciſeneſſe, let vs heare and obey our Sauiours counſell, Search<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 39.</note> the Scriptures, Ioh. 5. for they beare witneſſe of me, the Way, the Truth, the Life; they giue beſt teſtimony both of Gods will concerning his own ſeruice, and of his good will in Chriſt to all his faithfull ſeruants. Let this Word of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8100:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> God dwell plentifully in vs, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth,<note place="margin">Col. 3. 16.</note> Col. 3. and that not in ſome, but in all wiſedome, that we may thinke, ſpeake, and doe wiſely in all things. And for the better ſharpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our dimmed ſight in matters diuine, let vs not refuſe the eye-ſalue of our better inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened guides, but gladly accept thereof, that ſo by all theſe, and other good meanes, our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences being rightly informed, we may expreſſe the goodneſſe of them, by doing or not doing confidently what God hath commanded or prohibited. And to this end, that our hearts<note place="margin">Col. 2. 2, 16.</note> may bee comforted and eſtabliſhed in euery good ſaying and doing, wee are to lay faſt hold on that euerlaſting conſolation and good hope through grace which the Father hath giuen vs, Coloſ. 2. 2, 16. and by all ſpirituall aliments to preſerue and cheriſh that ſauing faith in vs, whereby we are perſwaded that our ſinnes are pardoned, and God in Chriſt reconciled to vs. This indeed is the root of a good conſcience, as hath been already ſhewed: and this, <hi>Beleeue in Chriſts blood,</hi> is the gracious powerfull Word whereby all conſciences are now ſtilled; as the<note place="margin">Luk. 19. Act. 16.</note> conſciences of <hi>Mary Magdalen, Zacheus, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and that Iaylor were ſuddenly and ſoundly thereby quieted.</p>
            <p>Now for the cheriſhing and confirming of this faith, the daily exerciſes of repentance and obedience are requiſite; and therefore to make vp the vprightneſſe of a good conſcience, wee are, in the ſecond place, to ſpeake of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8100:38"/> as moſt neceſſary thereunto, to wit, of repentance and obedience. Of repentance in mind, altering the thoughts from the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of ſinne; of repentance in heart, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for the committing of ſinne; of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in mouth, reprouing and controlling ſin; of repentance in the whole man, remoouing whatſoeuer is knowne to be amiſſe, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth fruits of amendment of life, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a worke impoſſible to nature, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace, and ſo ſlow in the working of grace, through the contradiction of our nature, that howſoeuer many profeſſe it, yet few practiſe it; but being rightly practiſed, it will make ſuch a diuiſion betwixt our perſons and our ſinnes, that by the repairing of the Image of God more and more in vs, we ſhall haue comfortable furtherance in the way to ſaluation. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt not be wanting to him, or ſcanting in him, that deſireth a good conſcience. For where there is no true repentance, there is no true faith; no true faith, no true Chriſt; no true Chriſt, no true remiſſion of ſinnes; no true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, no true peace of conſcience, grounded vpon the aſſured ſenſe and inward feeling of the ſame: But rather the grace of Chriſt redeeming the loue of the Father elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the comfortable fellowſhip of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt quieting the conſcience, is farre off from them which continue in their ſinnes, and ſtand out as rebels in their diſobedience againſt God.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:8100:38"/>
            <p>The rule is ancient and true, <hi>Bona conſcientia</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>non ſtat cum propoſito peccandi;</hi> a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot ſtand with a purpoſe of ſinning, or with irreſolution againſt ſinne, but is armed thorowout with a reſolute determination, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly and willingly to ſinne no more; accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it a mockery to cry <hi>Peccaui,</hi> and mourne for ſinnes paſt, with a meaning to ſinne againe in the like; yea, a moſt ridiculous folly, like to the Shipmans continuall labouring at the pumpe, without any care to mend the leake. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we deſire to liue in the lawfull peace of an vpright conſcience: ſo let it be our chiefeſt care to inure our ſelues to the practice of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and obedience. The practice of which, (to ſpeake briefly of them ioyntly) conſiſts not in pretending, as the manner of many is, a good heart, without fruits of amendment, for that is but vanity; or in making ſome outward ſhew of reformation, without purging the heart and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, for that is but hypocriſie; or in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing of ſinnes, to wit, of prodigality or prophaneneſſe in youth, for couetouſneſſe and Popery in age, for that is but irreligious mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But in an inward lothing from the heart, and an outward leauing in the courſe of our life, of all ſuch knowne ſinnes wherein we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly liued and delighted; and alſo in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of the heart, and conſtant indeuour in our life and conuerſation, to practiſe all duties of piety &amp; charity, which in our ſeuerall places and callings are required. Tis not ſufficient to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8100:39"/> put off the old man, to caſt away the weapons<note place="margin">Eph. 4 22.</note> of darkeneſſe, and to abhorre and remooue<note place="margin">Col. 3. 10.</note> what is euill: but we muſt put on the New man,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> take vnto vs the Armour of light, and cleaue to<note place="margin">Rom. 12 9.</note> that which is good. Tis commendable with the repentant Prodigall, to forſake our former rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> luxurious, and offenſiue liuing, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to our Fathers home; for this mends the matter: but it is much more comfortable and complete, after the ſhaking off of the ragges of ſinne, to put on the robes of Righteouſneſſe and Garments of Saluation; for this perfecteth the match, and accompliſheth the marriage betwixt Chriſt and vs: and heereby ſhall we giue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to others, and to our ſelues, and our owne ſoules, that we are penitent and obedient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſo bring wonderfull peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to our conſciences.</p>
            <p>For when a Chriſtian, inriched with theſe ſpirituall graces of true knowledge and faith, ſhall thus proceed in the carefull practice of theſe holy duties of repentance and obedience; then his conſcience, which otherwiſe would looke ſterne vpon him, begins to ſmile, to ſpeak ſweetly to him, to conuerſe amiably with him, to clap him on the backe &amp; applaud him, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly exhilarate and refreſh him. To which purpoſe S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes excellently, <hi>Vis, O</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>homo, ſemper epulari, vis nunquam triſtis eſſe? benè viue:</hi> Wilt thou, O man, neuer be ſad; wilt thou turne the whole yeere into a merry Chriſt-tide? liue well then. <hi>Fiat iuſtitia,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8100:39"/> 
               <hi>&amp; habebis pacem;</hi> Eſchew euill, and doe good;<note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 13.</note> and thou needeſt not ſeeke peace and enſue it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 11.</note> Pſal. 34. for peace will finde thee, and kiſſe righteouſneſſe whereſoeuer ſhee finds it. Doe Iuſtice, loue mercy, humble thy ſelfe, and walke with thy God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> did, Gen. 5. doing all things as in Gods ſight; For this is the direct<note place="margin">Micah 6. 8.</note> way to the obtaining and maintaining of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience comfortably good; the voyce of ioy and<note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 15.</note> deliuerance ſhall be in the Tabernacles of the righteous, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, and the worke of<note place="margin">Eſa. 32. 17.</note> Iuſtice ſhall bring peace and quietneſſe, Eſa. 32. and it cannot be otherwiſe, but that <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> the King of righteouſneſſe, which walkes ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, ſhould alſo be Prince of <hi>Salem,</hi> and walke confidently, peaceably, ſecurely. <hi>Synceritas Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſiod.</note> 
               <hi>mater eſt, ſine qua tranquillitas omnis, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtas eſt:</hi> Sincerity is the mother of true tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, and without it, all carnall reſt is as a dangerous Lethargie. Sincerity, as it is of all vertues the girdle, and moſt acceptable to God,<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 14.</note> whoſe vnfained obedience it implyeth, ſo it is moſt profitable in all dangers, trials, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to man, whoſe peace it worketh, and in whom it begetteth a Lyon-like boldneſſe, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh: The righteous is as bold as a<note place="margin">Pro. 28. 1.</note> Lyon. This cannot be put out of countenance by the falſe accuſations of ſlanderous tongues; it throweth them off, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the Viper from<note place="margin">Act. 28. 5.</note> his hand, vnhurt. This ſaith with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> I paſſe not for mans iudgement, 1. Cor. 4. and<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 3. Iob 31. 35.</note> with <hi>Iob,</hi> Though mine aduerſary would write
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8100:40"/> a Booke againſt mee, I would take it vpon my ſhoulder, and binde it as a crowne vnto mee. What made <hi>Iob</hi> ſo confident? Surely it was the vprightneſſe of his heart, his ſincere obedience and innocency, which he ſaith he will hold faſt<note place="margin">Iob 27. 6.</note> and not forſake, leſt his heart ſhould reprooue him, and his conſcience trouble &amp; checke him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Wherefore as hee that will ſaile ſafely, muſt looke as well to the balaſt of his Ship, as to his ſailes: So if you will ſaile ſafely in the Ship of a good conſcience, to the Port and Hauen of heauen; you muſt not onely looke, that there bee ſoundneſſe in your knowledge and faith, which are as ſailes hoyſted vp to make foorth for the prize; but alſo that there be ſincerity in your repentance and obedience, which are as the ſoules balaſt, to moderate her pace, leſt ſhee daſh againſt the Rocks of preſumption, and to this end vſe that ſafe and ſauing method by a learned Father preſcribed; When thou art<note place="margin">Aug.</note> tempted to ſinne, ſet before thee the weight of ſinne, the wound of conſcience, the wrath of God, which is as a flaming fire, and remember<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> that tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be vpon euery ſoule that ſinneth, Rom. 2. And let this be vnto thee a ſtrong bridle, and retentiue from vice; and againe, when thou beginneſt to bee weary and drowzy in Gods ſeruice, thinke vpon the bleſſed recompence of well-doing, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that to them which by continuance in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, ſeeke glory and honour, there ſhall be giuen eternall life and immortality; and let this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8100:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> be a ſharpe-pointed ſpurre and motiue vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Be timorous of doing euill and wrong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it offendeth God, though there were no hell to terrifie thee; bee ſtudious of executing Iuſtice, and doing well, becauſe it pleaſeth God, though there were no heauen to reward thee. But becauſe there is a reward in heauen for all well-deeded Chriſtians prepared, and ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as is life eternall, Rom. 6. A Kingdome<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note> that cannot be ſhaken, Heb. 12. and an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> immortall and vndefiled, 1. Pet. 1. Let<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> 
               <hi>intuitus mercedis;</hi> the view of this recompence, ſerue as the hand to winde vp the plummets, to continue the curious clocke-worke of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Now foraſmuch as the ſincerity of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian obedience conſiſts not only in rectifying our owne courſes, and doing good our ſelues; but alſo in repreſſing the euils of the time, &amp; in reforming the irregularities of others, as much as in vs lyeth: Giue mee leaue, I beſeech you (Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſomewhat heereupon, as the occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; I come not hither to play a prize, or to vent ſpleene; But a great doore and effectuall ſeemes to bee opened vnto me at this time, ſo that if euer I were, with Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<note place="margin">Reu. 1. 10.</note> on the Lords Day; I truſt, Gods Spirit is in me this Day of the Lord, moouing mee thus to ſpeake vnto you, and to complaine that this practical politicall part of Chriſtian obedience, in reproouing and repreſſing ſinne in others, is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8100:41"/> commonly neglected of all, eſpecially of thoſe whom it doth moſt concerne, I meane Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to whom, authority from God and the King is committed, if not with <hi>Phineas</hi> his zeale, to ſlay ſinners, <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> yet with <hi>Moſes</hi> his courage, to ſlay ſinne in groſſe offenders, <hi>ſaluo iure.</hi> But alas, how doe many luke-warme neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-paſſiue Magiſtrates now a-dayes ſlay it? (<hi>aures omnium pulſo, conſcientias ſinguloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conuenio;</hi> that is, I ſpeake to the eares of all in generall, and appeale to the conſciences of euery one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) Surely euen by being content with it, or elſe by yeelding conſent vnto it; If it were not ſo, why then are not the hurts of the daughter Iudah healed? why are not the breaches of this our Sion ſtopped vp? Is there no balme in Gilead, is there no Phyſician there? Yes, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians there are ſome, but the moſt like to <hi>Iobs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 13. 4.</note> friends, Phyſicians of no value; <hi>Rephaims</hi> by<note place="margin">Deut. 2. 20.</note> name, <hi>Zamzummims</hi> in deed, Deuter. 2. who wheras by their places and callings they ought to be patrones of peace and piety, and patternes of temperance and ſobriety, and as Leaders of the Vantgard, to ſtand in the forefront of Gods Battels, againſt all Canaanites and Canaanitiſh faſhions, which beare ſway in Towne &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; they either runne a race of like ryot with others, or goe a foraging or boot-haling for themſelues, not caring what become of the Ship of State in generall, ſo they may ſaue themſelues in the Pinnace or Cocke-boate of their owne fortunes in particular; not daring to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8100:41"/> ſtrike one ſtroke in the warre againſt Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Such as are ſeditious miſchiefe-plotting Papiſts, horrible blaſphemers, ſhameleſſe forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, incorrigible drunkards, and the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, lewd, licencious liuers; not daring, I ſay, to let them blood with the ſharpe Razor of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, much leſſe to giue them a downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right blow of condigne puniſhment for their ſinfull preſumption. It grieueth me to thinke, and I euen bluſh to ſpeake, how weakely the ſword of Iuſtice is, by the Paralyticke hands of theſe meale-mouthed Magiſtrates, brandiſhed againſt the friends of <hi>Baal, Balaam,</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> too.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Oh then for a <hi>Moſes</hi> in theſe dayes, to fetch<note place="margin">Exod. 17.</note> water from the rocke, teares from the eyes, yea, drops of blood from the hearts of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon drunkards, which carowſe mans blood in cans &amp; flagons, and hardned by impunity, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit daily outrages in Towne and Countrey! Oh for a <hi>Phineas,</hi> to runne reſolutely with the<note place="margin">Num. 25.</note> ſpeare of due cenſure and caſtigation, thorow the very heart, as I may ſay, of whoredome, and all filthy abomination! Oh for a <hi>Iehu,</hi> to<note place="margin">2. King. 9.</note> march on couragiouſly in the Lords buſineſſe, againſt truth-oppoſing poore-oppreſſing <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezabel,</hi> and all other idolatrous enemies of Gods ſanctuary! <hi>Magna quidem est in illa ſeueritate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>pietas, per quam tollitur peccandi libertas;</hi> Great god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe indeed is ſhewed in that ſeuerity, where many by the exemplary puniſhment of a few, are reſtrained of their ſinfull liberty, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8100:42"/>
            <p>My good Lords, your places of authority, and theſe exulcerate times of iniquity, require in you <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſpirit, <hi>Phineas</hi> his zeale, and <hi>Iehu's</hi> inuincible fortitude. Oh put them all on, as complete armour, ſutable to your calling and dignity. Brandiſh with heate and courage, the ſword of iuſtice againſt the very faces of Gods enemies. Eſpecially, let <hi>Romiſh Iezabel,</hi> howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<note place="margin">2. King. 9. 33.</note> ſhe be painted, not be ſpared, tumble her out at window, let Babylons brats no more bee dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed with, or dandled, but rather daſhed in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For they are meditating more miſchiefe, and it is to be feared, they will prouide more Powder, and poyſoned Kniues too, if they bee not fettered and manacled. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Yea but they haue now taken the Oath of alleageance, and will do no more hurt. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Yea but according to the rule of the Parthians, they will keepe faith with none, <hi>niſi quantum expedit,</hi> but as it ſerues their turne; and therefore looke from them no good: and as for Oathes, to the moſt of them they are no other then collars for Munkeyes, which vpon diſpenſation of ſuperiours, they ſlip off their neckes at their pleaſure, eſpecially if they bee ſuch State-Papiſts as haue beene inſpired with Ieſuiticall impoſtures, whom a Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Biſhop King.</note> of our Church rightly tearmeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the falſeſt coozeners of the world; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with whom no bond of nature, conſanguinity, alleageance, alliance, affiance, wedlocke, oath, Sacrament ſtandeth good, if they liſt to diſſolue it. <hi>Dij terrae
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8100:42"/> talem terris auertite peſtem.</hi> O yee Gods of the<note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6.</note> earth, purge I beſeech you, this Weſterne regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ayre, as much as in you lyeth, of theſe peſtilent exhalations; ſhake not onely the ſword of the Law againſt them, but lay it cloſe home vpon them, and let all ſuch as will not doe the<note place="margin">Ezra 7. 26.</note> Law of God and the King, receiue iudgement without delay, Ezra. 7.</p>
            <p>To conclude, foraſmuch (Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) as your comming forth in Circuit to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iuſtice and Iudgement, is like the comming forth of the foure Angels, Reuel. 7. to whom<note place="margin">Reuel. 7. 1.</note> power was giuen to puniſh the wicked of the earth, but with this reſtraint, that Gods Saints and ſeruants ſealed, ſhould not bee touched: or like the ariſing vp of foure Carpenters, Zech. 1.<note place="margin">Zech. 1. 20.</note> to cut off the foure hornes which ſcattered <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> that is, all the aduerſaries of the Church and Common-wealth, that the people of God might in peace and piety be the better maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. O rowze vp your ſelues, I beſeech you, in the name of God, of the Goſpell, of the King and Countrey, and with a zealous conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable affection, and a conſtant couragious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſhew your ſelues ſuch Angels, ſuch Carpenters, ſuch Worthies in oppoſing the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent ſtreame and torrent of theſe vicious times, and in executing iuſt and ſpeedy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on all malicious and ſeditious tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of the Lawes of God and the King: And for a percloſe of the premiſes heerein, exerciſe the vprightneſſe of your conſcience, and the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8100:43"/> ſincerity of your conſcionable obedience, <hi>viz.</hi> in cutting off, putting downe, or ſhutting vp all miſchiefe-practiſing-workers of iniquity, and all miſchiefe-plotting ſeeds-men, and fauourers of Schiſme and ſoule-murthering Popery.</p>
            <p>Thus by taking away the wicked from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Prou. 25. 4.</note> the King, his Throne in righteouſneſſe ſhall bee eſtabliſhed, your places of authority ſhall in their full ſtrength and vertue bee preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, Gods fierce wrath be turned away, which is imminent on Prince and people, where groſſe ſinnes paſſe vnpuniſhed, and the peace and piety of theſe quarters of the Land ſhall more and more bee increaſed. All which, the Lord grant, for his great mercies ſake, for his Goſpels ſake, for his Glories ſake, and for his Chriſts ſake; and ſo plentifully diſtill the ſweet dewes of his heauenly grace on the high Hill <hi>Hermon,</hi> and all the Mountaines of Sion, that there may be ſtill a fruitfull watering, and ioyfull refreſhing of this whole Land of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el: and that maugre the miſchieuous proiects and practices of the malignant enemies of the Goſpell, truth and peace may meet together, righteouſnes and mercy kiſſe each other, in all the quarters thereof, as long as the earth reſts in her Center, and the heauens continue their reſtleſſe motion.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:8100:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CONSCIONABLE CHRISTIAN:</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Preached at Taunton, Aug.</hi> 8. 1620.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text: Acts 24. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Heerein I indeuour my ſelfe, to haue a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alwayes towards God and men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOVRABLE, Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded and beloued in the Lord Ieſus, &amp;c. As good <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 20. 20.</note> in loue vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> (whom hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as his ſoule) did ſhoot three Arrowes of admonition, to driue him the further off from <hi>Sauls</hi> death-breathing fury: So in loue vnto your ſoules, I am now from the as-yet bent Bow of my Text, to ſend forth a third Arrow of inſtruction and direction, to draw you the neerer home to Gods life-giuing fauour. Whereof you ſhall be ſure to haue the ſtronger hold-faſt and aſſurance, by how much the more you indeuour and exerciſe your ſelues
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8100:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> in this, <hi>to haue alwayes a good conſcience towards God and men.</hi> For the care of a good conſcience brings comfort in holineſſe; and comfort in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, breeds aſſurance of bleſſedneſſe; and bleſſed ſhall you be, if to thoſe diuers Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents which concurre to the compoſition of an vpright conſcience, whereof yeſterday I ſpake at large, it ſhall pleaſe you to adde this as the complement of the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> perſeuerance in doing well, and cheriſhing the vertuous; and conſtant boldneſſe in repreſſing euill, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the vicious whereſoeuer you haue to doe; being as earneſt in the purſuit of groſſe ſinne, as worthy <hi>Eleazar</hi> was in ſmiting the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, 2. Sam. 23. and cleauing as faſt in your<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23. 10.</note> hearts to Gods Word, the warrant of your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing in this, as his hand claue vnto his ſword, the inſtrument of his well-doing in that. What if for your zeale and religious reſolution here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you be ſometimes croſſed with miſchieuous intentions, thwarted by mighty oppoſitions, wronged by malicious detractions? yet deſiſt not, faint not, feare not; <hi>Regium eſt, cùm benefece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alexander.</note> 
               <hi>malè audire:</hi> It is a princely thing, to heare ill, for doing well. In which courſe of well-doing, as I am bound to be a ſuiter vnto God for you, that your <hi>Bow may abide ſtrong, and that your hands</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 24.</note> 
               <hi>and armes may be ſtrengthened</hi> by the mighty God of <hi>Iacob:</hi> So, giue me leaue alſo, in the name of God, to be a bold ſollicitour vnto you, and for the Goſpels ſake, which you profeſſe, and are bound by your beſt actions to beautifie, now the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8100:44"/> third time to be your humble Monitor and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, that according to your places of command and greatneſſe, you would therein ſtriue with an holy kind of emulation, the more fully and freely to exerciſe your goodneſſe. And as it hath pleaſed God to indow you with greater meanes, power and ability, ſo to account it the beſt Chriſtian policy, by your good workes on earth, to lay vp treaſure for your ſelues in heauen, and euery day to bring in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what into Gods Exchequer, as the Iſraelites did<note place="margin">Exod. 25.</note> to the Tabernacle; the remembrance whereof may long after, both in life and death, comfort you, and whereof you may ſay (in ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence claiming an eſpeciall intereſt in Gods fauour, and expecting the promiſed recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence) <hi>Remember me, O my God, according to this:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 13. 22. Note. Math. 5. 26.</note> For albeit the glory of God muſt be the <hi>vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus terminus</hi> of our cogitations and actions, and the principall motiue of our good workes, and the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of our obedience; yet in the<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> actions of obedience, whileſt we ſeeke the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Gods glory in the firſt place, wee may as a ſecondary obiect or adiunct, reſpect<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> our owne commodity, and haue an eye to our eternall reward: yea, it is lawfull for euery ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Chriſtian (maugre the ſpirit of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in weaklings or wranglers) whileſt he remembreth God in ſincere obedience (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did in ſacrificing <hi>Iſaac; Moſes,</hi> in gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,<note place="margin">Gen 22. 1. King. 2. Luk. 7.</note> and going before Gods people; <hi>Obediah,</hi> in relieuing the Lords Prophets; <hi>Magdalen,</hi> in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8100:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> waſhing Chriſts feet; <hi>Dorcas,</hi> in making gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> for poore widowes; <hi>Philemon,</hi> in refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Epiſt. Philem. Nehem. 5. 19.</note> the bowels of the Saints; and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> in doing good to Gods Houſe and his people) to deſire God to remember him by a gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; and to ſay with <hi>Nehemiah, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 13. 22.</note> 
               <hi>me, O my God, concerning this;</hi> but yet as conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to himſelfe of many imperfections in his beſt actions, of defects and defaults, either in the end, matter, manner or meaſure of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, he is, as it followeth in the ſame place, to ſupplicate for mercy, and to pray, as there <hi>Nehemiah</hi> doth, But pardon me according to thy great mercy. For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Niſi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa. 100</note> 
               <hi>Deus per miſericordiam parceret, non inueniret quos per iuſtitiam coronaret:</hi> Except God ſhould ſpare vs in mercy, hee ſhould finde none whom hee might crowne in iuſtice. But yet in hope and expectation to be crowned in mercy, let vs all, as the Almners of the Almighty, remember daily to doe good in our ſeuerall callings, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ability, to be plentifull in the works of charity, to bee faithfull in the exerciſes of piety, that ſo our ſoules, as fields of ſincerity, being euery day more and more charged with the deeds of iuſtice and mercy, may at length be accompliſht with the Creſt and Crowne of eternall glory.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe tendeth the precept and charge of the Apoſtle, <hi>Be not weary of well doing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9. Eccl. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>for in due time yee ſhall reape, if you faint not:</hi> and that of <hi>Chryſoſtome, Sow with a mind to reape;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re imperf.</note>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:8100:45"/> 
               <hi>ſight, with a deſire to ouercome; conquer, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation to be crowned.</hi> Wherein Perſeuerance (which <hi>Bernard</hi> calleth, <hi>Sororem patientiae, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>filiam, pacis amicam, virtutuni conſummationem.</hi> And another, <hi>Talarem tunicam, that long white</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>Robe reaching downe to the feet,</hi> which euery good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> muſt put on: and another, The Empreſſe<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> of vertues, which rewardeth him that runneth, crowneth him that fighteth, bringeth to the hauen him that ſaileth; without which, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath no reward, a good turne receiues no thankes, and fortitude deſerues no glory.) Wherein, I ſay, perſeuerance in well-doing,<note place="margin">Note.</note> (which is euery Chriſtian mans duty) in hope and expectation of recompence, (conſidering our humane infirmity) is commended vnto vs all, and that not onely in our generall calling as we are Chriſtians, but alſo in our particular vocations, as wee are Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Iudges, Iuſticers, or any other inferiour bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall Officers in Church or Common-wealth. So that looking for the reward, not of debt, but of fauour (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) we are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> confidently and conſtantly in our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an obedience to the end. Yea, it is our duty to labour much to liue ſo; to ſuffer much to dye ſo, as conſtant conſcionable Chriſtians ought; yea, to dye in deſpight of death couragiouſly for the maintenance of equity and truth, to raigne ſo, as conſtant conſcionable Chriſtians vndoubtedly ſhall.</p>
            <p>Thus if we (Beloued) ſhall giue all diligence
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8100:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> to perſeuere in the practice of the generall and particular duties of Chriſtian obedience, wee ſhall then with daily comfort, taſte the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an vpright conſcience; and if we deſire and indeuour without diſſimulation and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, in reſpect of others, without partiality and defection, in regard of our ſelues, to walke in the wayes of Gods Commandements, as he hath preſcribed; wee ſhall bee ſure to inioy the continuall ioy and peace of a good conſcience, without night of deſertion, or eclipſe of change and variation, as he hath promiſed.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, if we (Fathers and brethren) according to the dictate and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of conſcience inlightened and awaked, ſhall both in the courſe of our generall conuerſation, and in the offices of our particular vocation, be carefull and faithfull, in louing what God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and hating what he hateth, in doing what God commandeth, and eſchewing what he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth, we ſhall then be both truely holy and happy too.</p>
            <p>So ſhall we be exempt and free, not onely from the crimſon-crying ſinnes of Iuſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wronging Magiſtrates, ſoule-ſtaruing Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, face-grinding oppreſſors, truth-betraying witneſſes and lurors, ſacrilegious rob-Gods, deſperate mocke-Preachers, and ſuch like flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious offenders, who with ſeared and benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med conſciences, <hi>habituati ſunt in malo, &amp; faetent in peccato;</hi> lie ſtinking in their ſinnes, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the graue: But alſo from the common ſinnes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8100:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> of wantons, gluttons, lyers, ſwearers, ſlanderers, Sabbath-breakers, and the like common ſinners, whoſe large cheuerill conſciences diſpenſe with all corruptions and tranſgreſſions that are not capitall: yea, we ſhall be free by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid godly care, from the vniuſt moroſity, and cauſeleſſe anxiety of ſcrupulous bird-eyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which make more Commandements then ten, and proiect fearefull things, where no feare is: That ſo our rightly-informed quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquitting conſciences may paſſe (with Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile and Banners diſplaid, with Flags of defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the workes and workers of iniquity) through the waues of this world, to the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of eternall reſt, ioy, and felicity.</p>
            <p>With ſuch a cleering-cheering conſcience,<note place="margin">Note.</note> our Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the worthy Champion<note place="margin">Acts 27. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 36.</note> of Ieſus Chriſt, ſailed couragiouſly in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Adriaticall Sea, when the tempeſtuous Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclydon raged, and meate and light was for many dayes denyed, and all that were in the Ship beſides deſpaired, telling them confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that none of them ſhould periſh, but all bee preſerued for his ſake. With the wings of ſuch a conſcience, when the Iewes thought &amp; ſpake<note place="margin">Acts 23. 24, 25.</note> euill of him, and plotted miſchiefe againſt him, he as an Eagle, ſoared aloft, and reſpecting their forged calumnies, no more then the chitting of Sparrowes or chatting of Pyes, bare himſelfe vp brauely aboue the ſcourges and razors of their tongues, and farre beyond the Sphere of their malignity; with this Armour of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8100:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> on the right hand, and the left being fitly cladde, he paſſed through good reports and bad, through many iniuries, indignities, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and difficulties, as bold as a Lyon, as vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant as <hi>Gideon</hi> and <hi>Samſon.</hi> A good conſcience, like the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> bare him vp aboue the pride and power of all worldly ſurges and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, vndaunted, vnappalled; ſo that at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night<note place="margin">Acts 16. 25.</note> in the dungeon, all manacled and fettered as hee was in a wounded skinne, wee find him praying and ſinging in a whole and merry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> could not be merry without a Muſician,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab,</hi> without <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, proud <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 21. Eſth. 7.</note> without <hi>Mordecais</hi> courteſie: But he that carryeth the true Electuary, <hi>exhilarans &amp; laetifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans Galeni,</hi> of a good conſcience about him, he hath ſelfe-ſufficiency, and without Muſicke, money, lands or honour, is happy ſtill, and merry alone, like to the late inuented Muſicall inſtruments of perpetuall motion, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>With this Counſeller and Comforter in the boſome, to wit, a good conſcience, <hi>Iacob</hi> can<note place="margin">Gen. 28. 11.</note> ſleepe ſweetly on a pillow of ſtone; <hi>Daniel</hi> and<note place="margin">Dan. 1. 15.</note> his fellowes looke freſh and faire, feeding on pulſe alone; <hi>Iob,</hi> in the midſt of his paine and pouerty, poſſeſſed of this true Diamond, which darted many beames of comfort vpon his ſoule, challenged his aduerſaries to write againſt him<note place="margin">Iob 31. 35, 36.</note> a Booke of ſlander, and hee would take it vpon his ſhoulder, &amp; bind it to his head as a Crowne of honour. Heereunto <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> neere vnto<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.</note>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:8100:47"/> death, hauing recourſe for ſuccour, confidently thus ſaith, I beſeech thee, Lord, remember how I haue walked before thee in truth. By this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor-hold, all the children of God, in the midſt of manifold temptations and ſpirituall conuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, haue beene euer ſo mainely ſuſtained, that with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> they haue thus conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued; Whether wee liue, we liue vnto the<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 8.</note> Lord; whether we die, we die vnto the Lord; whether we liue therefore or die, wee are the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Doe ye then (Men, Fathers, and Brethren) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue in your ſelues an heauen vpon earth, and to aſpire to an happineſſe, independant on the creatures without you? O then indeuour earneſtly, and purſue this one thing aboue other things, <hi>viz.</hi> the hauing and holding of an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right conſcience within you. Doe all things as in Gods preſence, cheriſh true ſauing-faith, by often hearing and reading of the Word, and the frequent practice of Prayer and true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, inure your ſelues by religious exerciſes, to a kind of familiarity with God, that the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of his loue in Chriſt, and the comforts thereof be not interrupted, walke carefully in your particular callings, to the glory of God and the common good, auoyding as ſerpents, couetouſneſſe and ambition, which make men ſet their conſciences on tenters, and ſtretch like cheuerill, and becauſe at the great and generall Aſſiſes, ſentence ſhall paſſe, and Iudgement be awarded, according to the things written in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8100:48"/> Booke of euery mans conſcience; take we heed<note place="margin">Reu. 20. 13.</note> that theſe Bookes of account bee kept vnblur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vnpolluted, pure and cleane from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſinnes, which are the cut-throate of the ſoule, and offenſiue in Gods ſight. In a word; let this be your wiſh aboue all wiſhes, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in make ſure worke (come of the reſt what will) that by the effuſion of Chriſts Blood for you, and infuſion of his Spirit into you, you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy this pleaſant and peaceable portion of a good conſcience, which is more highly to bee eſteemed of, and held at a dearer rate, then the Merchants precious Pearle, for which (as it is<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 46.</note> in the Parable) he ſold all that he had; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon whereof, the things that are in the worlds eye moſt aduantageable vnto vs, are to be accounted loſſe, and iudged as dung, that we<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 7.</note> may win it. Let others ſay, Who wil ſhew vs any good? Yet, Lord, lift thou vp the light of thy<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> countenance vpon vs. Let others content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a portion in this life, whoſe bellies<note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 14, 15.</note> thou filleſt with thy hid treaſure; but let vs (O Lord) behold thy face in righteouſneſſe, and in the glaſſe of a good conſcience heere on earth: ſo when we awake in the day of Reſurrection, we ſhall be ſatisfied with thine Image, rauiſhed with ſeeing, and ſecured for retaining thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence in heauen.</p>
            <p>All earthly ioyes and treaſures, without this of a good conſcience, are but as ſo many pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous waights, to giue poize to the ſoule to ſinke it to hell. But with this, all outward helpes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8100:48"/> for preſent maintenance, are as ſo many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooters and Proctors for the future inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, giuing vs not onely wings of a Doue or an Eagle, but of an Angel, to aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>With this heauenly treaſure then of an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right conſcience, whoſoeuer amongſt vs (O that there were many ſuch!) is really poſſeſſed, to ſpeake plainely in the phraſe of the holy Ghoſt, he is (without controuerſie) richly, yea, royally bleſſed. <note n="*" place="margin">Sola conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia virtutum praeſtat gaudium verum &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum. Caeterae hilarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes frontem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittunt, cor non implent. Sen. in Ep. 23.</note> Hee need not enuy the rich Corne-hoorders barnes inlarged, and goods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, or the Gluttons purple rayment and delicious feeding, or the greatneſſe of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Potentate, arrayed in robes of State, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with Pearle, and boaſting with <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> of his power and ſtately building; No: Hee need not enuy the magnificent pompe, and vſurped Oecumenicall power of that triple-crowned ruffling Prieſt of Rome (that <hi>Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus Daemon,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> calls Antichriſt) who to giue life to the image of the Beaſt, ſeekes, as<note place="margin">Reu. 13. 15.</note> much as in him lieth, to make the Lord of life, <hi>exhaeredem vineae, exhaeredem vitae;</hi> riding on mens ſhoulders, treading on Emperours necks, and ſwimming in his Orcipotent Sea, with the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of intolerable pride and inſolency. No, no: <hi>Vix vnius aſsis—Nec pretio pluris mundana haec omnia ducit;</hi> For carryed in the triumphant Chariot of a cleare conſcience, and aduanced farre aboue theſe painted Pageants of things ſublunary and periſhing, with Gods leaue and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8100:49"/> loue he inioyeth a ſelfe-ſufficient happineſſe in health and ſickeneſſe, in life and death, and after death euer-induring.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> O happy then, and thrice happy we, if as S.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> was, ſo our reioycing and glory bee in the teſtimony of a good conſcience! if in truth wee can doe as in all his tryalls he did, hold foorth this teſtimony as a ſhield of defence, and flag of defiance, againſt all ſcandalous imputations and<note place="margin">Acts 23. &amp; 24. &amp; 25.</note> aſperſions; if we can truely ſay as he ſaid; Wee are aſſured that we haue a good conſcience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring in all things to liue honeſtly, Heb. 13. 18. or duely indeuour, as hee in my Text indeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>to haue a good conſcience alwayes towards God</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text. 3. part.</note> 
               <hi>and men.</hi> Which words importing the latitude or extent of a good conſcience, in reſpect of time, and the obiects thereof, come now very fitly to bee handled, wherein I will labour to preuent your wearineſſe. Firſt, of the time, and duration of the Apoſtles indeuour and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe to haue a good conſcience, namely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Alwayes,</hi> being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the<note place="margin">Alwayes.</note> Scholiaſt hath it, being in all things euery man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way (ſo farre as humane frailty did not let) inoffenſiue and vnblameable, indeuouring at all times, through the whole tenor of his life, <hi>Non pro vſura exigui temporis, aut pro primis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>tantum diebus, ſed omnibus diebus vitae poſt conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> as <hi>Caluin</hi> renders it, to bee vprightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable, conſcionably vpright.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>8</label> So that this word (<hi>Alwayes</hi>) imports con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie and equality, without remiſſeneſſe or
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8100:49"/> partiality. In the life of man and courſe of his calling, there are many turnings, references, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, opportunities, importunities, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reſpects; in all which, at euery turne to bee the ſame man, requires the ſtrength of a good conſcience. A child or weakeling may take two or three ſteps well, and walke ſomewhat euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but to turne hither and thither, vp and downe with actiueneſſe and dexterity, and to maintaine the thorow pace or race with ſettled conſtancie and alacrity, argues the metall and making of a very ſtrong man. Such an one was our Apoſtle in the race of Chriſtianity after his conuerſion, as appeareth by his Triumphant <hi>Epinichion,</hi> 2. Tim. 4. I haue fought a good fight,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 7.</note> kept the faith, finiſhed my courſe, &amp;c. and by his confident proteſtation, Acts 23. 1. I haue<note place="margin">Acts 23. 1.</note> ſerued God with a good conſcience <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thorowout vnto this day. Alwayes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtumbling, without offence, as it is in my Text, &amp;c. Which is not ſo preciſely to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,<note place="margin">Reaſ. double.</note> as if he had beene alwayes indowed with an equall good diſpoſition to godly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and had neuer ſlipt or ſlept through humane infirmity; For as the Spouſe of Chriſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<note place="margin">Cant. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of her ſelfe, I ſleepe, but my heart waketh: and ſo condemneth her drowzineſſe in the fleſh, notwithſtanding her watchfulneſſe in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. So S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7. complaineth on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7. 19.</note> that (in regard of the combate which is betwixt the fleſh and the Spirit, in the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate) he did ſometimes the euill hee would
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8100:50"/> not, and did not at other times the good hee would, and ſo was vnwillingly defectiue, through natures frailty and weakneſſe, but yee not wittingly offenſiue, through ſins malignity and peruerſenes. For the power of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce preſerued him ſo vpright, that as a ſquare Cube, or <hi>homo quadratus,</hi> he was the ſame, which way ſoeuer he were turned: to God, or man; to company, or himſelfe alone; vpon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and occurrences he held his owne, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alwayes, in all things, to walke honeſtly, Heb. 13. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> It is farre otherwiſe, God knowes, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhewes, in too many now adayes, which haue weake crazy conſciences, and as diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red braines, their <hi>turbida &amp; lucida interualla,</hi> their good and euill dayes: who, like <hi>Mercury</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Planets, are of a variable conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, faſt and looſe, ſtrict in ſome things, looſe in other; godly in one company, and prophane in another; vp and downe, off and on, in and out, almoſt at euery turne; who can indifferently brooke all companies, and conuerſe with all manner of perſons. If they be ruffians, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, drunkards, they can play the good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes with them. If they be good men, which feare God, they will diſcourſe of poynts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and adioyne themſelues to their ſociety; as if there were good agreement betwixt light and darkneſſe, righteouſneſſe and vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, God in the one, and <hi>Belial</hi> in the other. To ſpeake to the preſent occaſion; In the cauſe and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8100:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> caſe of <hi>Titius</hi> their kinſman, or rich friend and neighbour, they can be preciſe and peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forward by all meanes to promote it: But in as good a ſuite and iuſt a cauſe of <hi>Sempronius</hi> a ſtranger, or meane-ſtated-man, they will bee retchleſſe and remiſſe, not caring how hee bee wronged in it. I would to God the conſciences of more then a good many of our Magiſtrates were not ſuch; but commonly ſuch they are, who though they profeſſe and pretend, that in places of Iudicature they will heare the ſuites of poore and rich with equall patience and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, examine and cenſure all controuerſies indifferently without preiudice, partiality, and needleſſe protraction; yet when it comes to proofe, they prooue farre otherwiſe, and like in truth to a fiſhing rod, which ſtandeth ſtraight when a Menow, or Gogin, or ſmal fiſh is taken; but boweth and bendeth, and the line ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times breaketh too, when a Peale or great fiſh is to be drawne vp: So when the Law hath can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſed and caught a poore man, being perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the rich, then iuſt Iudgment proceedeth ſpeedily; but when the rich and mighty ones are haply taken in their ouer-takings and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe dealings, and brought within compaſſe of the Lawes cenſure; then (O cruell pity!) there is much yeelding, bending, bowing, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times breaking too, to free them from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty and vigour of the Law, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Neither is this the fault only of ſome chiefe Magiſtrates and miniſters of iudgement, but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8100:51"/> the vſuall preuarication of many mercenary Lawyers, Iurors, witneſſes, and ſuch like inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Iuſtice, whoſe weake conſciences, at the command of gaine or greatneſſe, (as at the view of <hi>Meduſaes</hi> ſtupifying head) either ſtretch as Chiuerell in the raine, or ſhriuell vp as parchment againſt the fire, and ſo giue way, if not warrant, to the works of iniuſtice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by innocency is wronged, good lawes are delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, godly men diſ-heartened, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſhonoured.</p>
            <p>And here I could open a myſtery of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſhew <hi>quibus apicibus &amp; appendicibus iuris, innocens torquetur à cauſidico, dum cauſa torquet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem:</hi> that is, with what quirkes and trickes the innocent party is by the Lawyer wrung and put to the worſt, notwithſtanding the goodnes of his cauſe, and the Law it ſelfe hath driuen his aduerſary to the wall. Yea, I could iuſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh againſt the dreadfull licence of inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces amongſt our Engliſh pleaders in caſes cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall; whereby it often comes to paſſe, that vpon very nice poynts innocents haue bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; as <hi>Edward</hi> Earle of Warwick was in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenths dayes, and the Duke of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixths, &amp;c. Yea, I could here exhibit a bill of wofull complaint, in the name of many poore, impotent, innocent men and women: Firſt, againſt thoſe aduocates, which with their Clyents great coſt, and their owne ſmall conſcience, maintaine contentions, becauſe contentions maintaine them, and by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8100:51"/> Engliſh delayes, worſe then Spaniſh Strapados,<note place="margin">Marnix.</note> protract their ſuits in Law, till they bee non-ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of life. Secondly, againſt thoſe Iurates and witneſſes, which without heed-taking to their hearts, that they conceiue no malice; to their hands, that they receiue no bribes; to their eares, that they heare no falſe accuſation; to their eyes, that they ſee no wrong; to their feet, that they be not ſwift to ſhead blood (as if all theſe outward ſenſes of the body, and the inward powers of the ſoule too were wholly corrupted) doe, without care or conſcience, feare of God, or reuerence of man, giue either<note place="margin">Prou. 19. 28.</note> vniuſt verdict in the cauſe, or falſe euidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſons of their brethren and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, euen as by their paſſions they are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwayed,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 21.</note> or ouerwaighed by the purſe, or by their friends intreated, or by their fellowes in<note place="margin">Exod. 23. 2.</note> euill perſwaded. Theſe are ſores which had need to be lanced, that in time they might bee cured. But becauſe your Honours haue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſome degrees of roundneſſe againſt theſe inormities as you meet with them in your Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, reſounding onely in your eares what the Smith did in the <hi>Lantſgraues,</hi> when (he thought him too mild) <hi>Dureſcite dureſcite,</hi> for, <hi>immedicabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vulnus-Enſe recidendum eſt, ne pars ſyncera traha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> I here refraine from further agitation of them, or exclamation againſt them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, not ceaſing yet to admoniſh in generall, all ſuch as finde themſelues guilty of ſo corrupt dealings and curſed doings, that they blot out
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8100:52"/> of the booke of conſcience, their ſinnes by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and by vnfained ſorrow of humbled contrite hearts, deprecate the iudgements due vnto them for the ſame; and for the time to come, beware of doing more harme to a man for a little pelfe, then euer they can doe him good againe with all their policy or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Beware of cutting aſunder the ſinewes of the Common-wealth, and of poyſoning the pure breath it drawes, by peruerting Iuſtice, and abuſe of the Lawes. Take heede by the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy end of <hi>Ahab</hi> and his ſeed, that yee ſeeke<note place="margin">1. King 21. 20.</note> not, vnder colour of Law, to rob your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his field and life: For though <hi>Naboth</hi> thy neighbour be dead, and cannot be reuenged of thee, yet thy conſcience, the Lords Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, will meet thee, as <hi>Elias</hi> did <hi>Ahab,</hi> and tell thee, Thou haſt ſold thy ſelfe to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe abominable, and bring thee tidings of vengeance vnauoydable. Be warned by the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall iſſue of <hi>Iudas</hi> his treaſon, that (either to<note place="margin">Math. 27. 5.</note> pleaſe others, or to profit your ſelues) yee dare not be agents or inſtruments of betraying an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: For after the fact, when your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſhall (as ſooner or later they will) vex and gall you for it, and make your liues more irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to you, then the moſt violent death; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you runne for comfort and reliefe in this agony? will you returne to your great friends, for whoſe pleaſure you did it, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did to the high Prieſts and Elders for fauour, when he had ſold his Maſter? Alas, they will
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8100:52"/> reuile you, and leaue you diſconſolate; and when in anguiſh of ſpirit you ſhall confeſſe as<note place="margin">Note.</note> hee did, that you haue ſinned in betraying the Innocent, they will deſperately reply (as not touched with the ſinne themſelues procured and hired) <hi>What is that to vs? looke thou to it?</hi> Haſt thou forſworne thy ſelfe in my cauſe, thou vnconſcionable Iuror? haſt thou applyed thy wit and tongue to maintaine and follow my lawleſſe ſuite, thou corrupt Lawyer? Haſt thou, for lucre or fauour, ſtretcht thy conſcience to doe wrong in a matter of forgery, thou falſe witneſſe? What is that to me? looke thou to it? Thus if you deale hollowly with God for mens fauours, you ſhall finde them in need but hollow friends, yea, miſerable comforters. Whither next will you betake your ſelues for ſuccour, for helpe, for remedy? What, to the money, or worldly benefit gotten by this tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, or purchaſed by that villany? Indeed the thirty pieces of ſiluer, were <hi>Iudas</hi> his <hi>Thamar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.</note> the delight of his ſoule, and longing of his thoughts, vntill his wickedneſſe was acted; but afterwards feeling that hee had dearely bought them, by betraying his Maſter to death, his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to deteſtation, and his ſoule to damnation, he tooke no ioy in them, as an execrable thing he abandoned them; yea, he hated them more<note place="margin">Math. 27. 5.</note> then he loued them before, and could not bee quiet till hee had thruſt them out at doore, as <hi>Amnon</hi> did <hi>Thamar;</hi> and caſt them downe in the Temple, as the witneſſe of his ſinne, and the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8100:53"/> burthen of his ſoule, and ſo departing hanged himſelfe:</p>
            <q>Dignum opus authore; eſt dignus &amp; ipſe opere.</q>
            <p>Sith then neither your friends, nor your gaine gotten by guile, nor (to bee briefe) any other worldly hopes or helpes can comfort you; but rather will bee corroſiues to you, when your conſciences awaked ſhall ſting you for your wrongfull miſ-dealings with thoſe in whoſe matters you haue had to doe; what refuge now remaineth for you? Will you now at laſt caſt fly to God for redreſſe, in this your diſtreſſe? It is likely (ſuch is mans preſumption) you will make ſo bold an aduenture. But alas, there can be ſmall hope of aduantage heereby: for God will not ſo eaſily bee intreated to pleaſure you, ſith you haue ſo eaſily condiſcended in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the diuell and your owne luſts to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him: but as he ſent the Iſraelites in their<note place="margin">Iudg. 10. 14.</note> extremity, to the Idols which they had choſen, ſaying, Now let them deliuer you: So will hee ſend you to your wicked policies, plots and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, which you haue preferred before his counſels and Commandements, and bid you ſeeke helpe (but all in vaine) from them: yea, your owne Monitor in the boſome, will deliuer that fearfull meſſage to you, which <hi>Samuel</hi> did<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 26.</note> to <hi>Saul, Thou haſt forſaken the Lord, and the Lord hath forſaken thee.</hi> You haue ſaid, whileſt you were in the purſuit of your ſinnes, to the Holy one of Iſrael, Depart from vs, we deſire not the<note place="margin">Iob 21. 14.</note> knowledge of thy wayes. Therfore, now when
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8100:53"/> the horrour of your ſinnes vnrepented purſueth you, he will be euen with you, and ſay, <hi>Depart</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7. 23.</note> 
               <hi>from me, ye workers of iniquity, I know you not.</hi> O conſider this in your owne ſoules, and refuſe not in time to bee made wiſe for your ſelues! Hearken to the counſell of <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Syrach:</hi> Say not, O man, thus and thus haue I<note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 4.</note> done, and yet no euill hath come vnto me; for though the Almighty bee a patient rewarder, yet he will not leaue thee vnpuniſhed: neither ſay, I haue enough for my life, I haue ſtrength, and who will bring me vnder for my workes? for God the auenger will reuenge the wrongs done by thee. And although haply thou art ſo in grace with the greateſt, and ſo eminent in place and authority, that thou thinkeſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by thee wronged, dare not lift vp a finger againſt thee; yet for all thy ſecurity, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not how neere thou art to ruine and miſery: For the wronged innocents, beſides a good and iuſt King on earth, haue alſo a rightfull Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in heauen, and ſuch an one as hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a reuenging eye and hand too, who will one day take the matters of the fatherleſſe, widowes, and poore Innocents into his owne hands, when there ſhall be a new inqueſt; and what hath bin heere put off, ſhuffled vp, and partially iudged, ſhall then be ſentenced and iudged againe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Iudges, Counſellours, Iurors, and all inferiour Officers themſelues: And as they, or any of them haue ſowne in hardneſſe of heart, ſo ſhall they reape in horrour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8100:54"/> 
               <hi>&amp; quorum oculos culpa clauſit, poena aperiet:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> and as they haue liued vnconſcionably by the Law, ſo ſhall they dye vncomfortably without Goſpell. Yea, leſt any obdurate forehead, whoſe reſolution can laugh his ſinnes out of countenance; or any wilfull peruerter of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Eccl. 8. 11.</note> and perſecutor of the poore and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſhould prophanely thinke, that God hath loſt his power, or left his prouidence, becauſe he doth not preſently execute Iudgement on an euill worke: <hi>Nouerint vniuerſi:</hi> Be it knowne to all ſuch workers of euill, that euen in this life God will right or reuenge the iniuries and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities of his poore oppreſſed diſtreſſed ones; and when, in the anguiſh of their ſoules, they ſhall cry vnto him, <hi>Exurgat Deus,</hi> Pſal. 68. Let<note place="margin">Pſal. 68. 1.</note> God ariſe: He, with an Ecchoes readineſſe will reply, <hi>Surgam,</hi> Pſal. 12. I will ariſe. For the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the needy, &amp; the ſighes of the poore I will vp (ſaith the Lord) and deliuer them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 12. 5.</note> Yea, though the poore-oppreſſed ſwallow vp their griefe in ſilence, &amp; cry not for vengeance, yet <hi>res ipſa clamabit,</hi> the hire of the labourers<note place="margin">Iam. 5. 4.</note> detained, Iam. 5. The blood of <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Naboth</hi> ſpilled, 1. King. 21. The ſtone and beame, by<note place="margin">Gen. 4. Habak. 2. 11.</note> fraud and violence placed in the houſe of the mighty oppreſſour, ſhall cry out for vengeance againſt him, who hath made his field <hi>Acheldama,</hi> and his houſe <hi>Golgotha</hi> (building it with the goods of the poore, painting it with the blood of the poore, and hanging it about with the skinnes of the poore, and (as I may ſay) vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propping
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8100:54"/> it with the bones of the poore.) And ſurely God ſhall be auenged on him, as hee was on <hi>Cain, Ahab, Iezabel;</hi> and not onely auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the great and mighty ill-man himſelfe (who hath diſcharged conſcience from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon his ground, and ſacrilegiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudes himſelfe on Church Demaines, and fleſhed therein, runnes with open mouth on the Commons of the Countrey) but alſo on all ſuch vniuſt Magiſtrates, * ſuborned Witneſſes,<note place="margin">Amos 2. Pro. 19. 5. Pro. 21. 28. Pſal. 140. 11.</note> corrupt Iurors, truth-outfacing Lawyers, cruell vnder-Sheriffes, and cunning Sollicitors, as haue aſſiſted him in his bloody conqueſt, and triumph ouer his harmeleſſe, helpeleſſe, diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Miniſter, Tenant, neighbour. Yea, more then ſo, in the 26. of Leuit. and 28. of Deut.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> you ſhall finde a large patrimony of fearefull plagues entayled to the very poſterity of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable peruerters of iudgement, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the innocent, and practiſers of violence or villany, and as well the Authours as Actors, the Plotters as Practiſers of miſchiefe, ſhall come to extreme miſery. The mouth of the<note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 20.</note> Lord hath ſpoken it, and his hands will bring it to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> O heare then and feare this, all ye that are, or haue beene any way imbarked in ſuch ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, breake off your ſinnes by repentance, and renew your reconciliation with God, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing and diſclaiming the matter of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betwixt him and you, and in all cauſes cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall and controuerſiall, which ſhall paſſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:8100:55"/> thorow your hands, or come to your hearing, euidencing, and ſentencing heereafter, learne and labour to haue and diſcharge a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience then you haue done heretofore. Whilſt the Flood-gate of Gods loue is opened, and his mercy ſtands and knockes at your gates for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, be intreated, leſt otherwiſe Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lay ſiege to your houſes and hearts too, and with terrour of minde you bee conſtrained to doe iuſtly: be iealous ouer your ſelues, with a godly iealouſie; be ſuſpicious of your owne deſires, of the cuſtomes of the times, of the policies of the world, and of thoſe ſinfull baites which Satan couers cunningly, that the hooke of inſuing dangers may not be ſeene, and let none of them intice you to ſay thus vnto your ſoule, Goe to now, for this once let ſuch a man in ſuch a matter be gratified, though againſt equity: but in the point of Iuſtice, ſhew your ſelues ſtrict and rigorous, inflexible, inexorable, like to that Roman <hi>Cato, à quo nemo rem iniuſtam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut.</note> 
               <hi>petere audebat:</hi> or <hi>Fabritius, qui nec audire nec vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quicquam turpe ſuſtinebat;</hi> and with a full and free-hearted renunciation of all iniuſtice, wrong, and violence. Herein ſeriouſly exerciſe your ſelues to haue and keepe <hi>Alwayes,</hi> euery day, and in euery action of the day, in all places, high or low, publike or priuate, in all caſes of rich or poore, great or ſmall, a good and vpright conſcience. It was S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Crowne of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 2.</note> that he could truely ſay, I haue wronged no man, corrupted no man, defrauded no man;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8100:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> and it was <hi>Samuels</hi> comfort, that he could cleere<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.</note> himſelfe, and that the people with free accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation did cleere and acquit him from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, 1. Sam. 12. And it was likewiſe the very ioy of <hi>Moſes</hi> heart, that he could affirme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, he had done no man hurt, Num. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. And doubtleſſe, this alſo will be a ſingular ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace to your ſoules, and an heauen to your hearts (Fathers and Brethren) when you ſhall lie on your beds ſickly, or in health conferre with your ſoules ſecretly, that (howſoeuer you may be otherwiſe traduced, as <hi>Moſes</hi> by the<note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> ſonnes of Belial was vniuſtly charged) yet you can waſh your hands with <hi>Dauid</hi> in innocency,<note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 6.</note> and your conſciences can tell you, without ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or flattery, that you haue wittingly wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no man, defrauded no man, beene corrupted by no man.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Which comfortable teſtimony of a good conſcience, that you (Right Honourable, and Right Worſhipful) may <hi>Alwayes</hi> haue and hold, (to come once more with a freſh charge vpon your ſoules) mine humble admonition, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from vnfained affection, ſhall be this, That ſith the Lord knoweth your downe-ſitting and<note place="margin">Pſ. 139. 1, 2, 3.</note> vp-riſing, and your thoughts long before, and is (together with his Deputy conſcience) priuie to all your wayes and workes, (all things being<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 13.</note> naked before him with whom we haue to doe, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, Heb. 4.) you would be carefull therefore and circumſpect to do, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer<note place="margin">Eccles. 9. 10.</note> your hand hath to doe, with all your
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8100:56"/> power, and that in ſimplicity and ſincerity, as in the ſight of God, and in his preſence, from whom nothing can be hid. <hi>Caue, ſpectat Cato,</hi> was an ancient Watch-word among the Romanes, and a great retentiue from vice. How much more ought this to be amongſt Chriſtians, <hi>Caue, videt Dominus?</hi> The forgetfulneſſe whereof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 13, 14.</note> makes many men, eſpecially great Ones, to dig deepe, as if they would hide their counſell from<note place="margin">Iſa. 29. 15.</note> the Lord; to worke in darkeneſſe, as if none ſhould or could ſee them, and politickly, as they deeme it, but dangerouſly, as the euent prooues it, to contriue in ſecret thoſe things, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward being brought to light, caſt ſhame in their faces, a burthen on their conſciences, a blot on their name; and without repentance, euerlaſting confuſion vpon body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>But I hope, this Lethargy and deadly ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe * hath no way indangered your ſoules, but<note place="margin">Temerita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aut timiditas Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, vel fauoribus corrupti, vel pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoribus territi, eſt calamitas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentis, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio iuris, proditio plebis. Saluian.</note> that they are euer awaked with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Gods preſence, in all your actions and cenſures of vindictiue or remuneratiue Iuſtice: ſo that the reward of vertue is not made a gift of ſauour, to pleaſure friends; or the puniſhment of vice, a meanes of reuenge, to confound enemies: but mercy and iudgement are in their due place and time, according to the rules of equity, executed by you, with a mind of Iuſtice to doe right vnto all.</p>
            <p>Thus I hope the beſt things of you: and therefore giue me leaue, for my farther and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler aſſurance therein, to vſe the ſame words
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8100:56"/> ſomewhat inlarged vnto you, which <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> did vnto the Iudges of his time; Take heed<note place="margin">2. Chr. 19. 6, 7.</note> what you doe, ye execute not the iudgements of man, but of the Lord; the ſeate wherein you ſit, is his; the people which you iudge, are his; the authority wherby ye iudge, is deriued from him. Take heed therefore that your paſſions ſway you not, that your friends preſſe you not, that your followers perſwade you not (in hope of bribes) to peruert Iuſtice: for though the Maſter be ſo iuſt with <hi>Eliſha</hi> to refuſe them, yet<note place="margin">2. King. 5.</note> commonly the ſeruant is ſo wicked with <hi>Gehaſi</hi> to receiue them. Take heed what you doe, for the Lord will bee with you in the cauſe and iudgement; great matters doe euer require great deliberation; weighty cauſes, weighty conſideration; ſerious buſineſſe, ſerious care and circumſpection. Take heed then what you doe, be guided by Gods Law, imitate his ſteps, haue no reſpect of perſons in iudgement, feare not the face of any man, but let the feare of the<note place="margin">Deut. 10. 18. Iſa. 11. 5.</note> Lord (with whom is no defect, no obliquity, no partiality, no iniquity) bee vpon you, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, as at all times, ſo eſpecially in Iudiciall places, God is preſent with you, and vieweth narrowly all your doings: hee ſtandeth in the<note place="margin">Pſal. 81. 1.</note> aſſembly of Gods (ſuch are yee <hi>nuncupatiuè</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but yee ſhall die like men, ſo fraile yee are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Wherefore take heed what ye doe, and make account this day, that yee ſhall one day render an account for whatſoeuer yee haue done, before that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:8100:57"/> Iudge of all the world, which iudgeth all righteouſly. O then gird vp your loynes with Iuſtice, and put on Righteouſneſſe for an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergeon: Iudge not according to the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,<note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 24.</note> but iudge righteous iudgement, and let the fire of zeale, for truth and equity, be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled, that the Oyle of mercy be not vtterly conſumed.</p>
            <p>Suffer not an <hi>Abimelech,</hi> vpon the malicious<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6. 22.</note> accuſation of a <hi>Doeg,</hi> to be deſtroyed; or a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 3.</note> vpon the pick-thanke inſinuation of a <hi>Ziba,</hi> to be ſpoiled; or a <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> vpon a wanton<note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> Miſtreſſes allegation, to bee impriſoned; or a <hi>Naboth,</hi> vpon <hi>Iezabels</hi> letter, to bee depriued<note place="margin">1. King. 21.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vineae &amp; vitae.</hi> But heare the cauſes of your Brethren without preiudicate impiety; iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly examine them without ſiniſter obliquity; and ſincerely iudge them without vniuſt partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity:<note place="margin">Deut. 1. 17.</note> and laying aſide all reſpect of perſons and popularity, according to the Lords Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Deut. 1. Let the cauſe of the poore and needy come in equall ballance with the rich and mighty; deferre not the hearing and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of their ſuites, from day to day, from Terme to Terme, leſt it fare with them, as it did with the <hi>Haemor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſe,</hi> Mark. 5. which was diſeaſed<note place="margin">Mark. 5. 25.</note> 12. yeeres together, and when ſhe had ſpent all on Phyſicians, was not awhit the better: or as it did with the weake perſon, Ioh. 5. which had<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 5.</note> beene diſeaſed eight and thirty yeeres, and ſate in the porch of the poole of Betheſda, but might not be healed, becauſe (for want belike
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8100:57"/> of ſtirring Angels) hee could get none to put him into the poole immediately after the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel had ſtirred it. For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, The gift<note place="margin">Pro. 18. 16.</note> of a man inlargeth him, and bringeth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great men: that is, maketh roome for him, and procureth him acceſſe to the preſence of ſuch as are in authority; whereunto the poore, by reaſon of penny-peeking pull-backes, may not approch. Well, whatſoeuer they cannot ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect for want of meanes, performe yee in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of mercy, pitty their caſes, regard their complaints in loue to God, and God with<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 17.</note> his all-ſufficient loue will certainely repay all your loue ſhewed to them.</p>
            <p>And as for bribery, the bane of all truth and<note place="margin">Amos 5. 12.</note> equity, worthy to be rewarded with <hi>Gehaſies</hi> leproſie, if it dare at any time to draw neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, O caſt it off from you, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the<note place="margin">Acts 27.</note> Viper from his hand; and as <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Simon</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.</note> 
               <hi>Magus</hi> his preſent, with indignation of heart; For fire ſhall deuoure the houſes of Bribes, Iob<note place="margin">Iob 15. 34.</note> 15. Contemne the wedge of gold, the molten Calfe, which ſo many worldly Idolaters crouch vnto: Abhorre the gathering of riches by a<note place="margin">Pro. 21. 6.</note> deceitfull tongue, which is a vanity toſſed to and fro of them that ſeeke death. Remember the end of <hi>Balaams</hi> wages and <hi>Iudas</hi> his Bagge, and Beware; ſell not thy countenance, thy tongue, thy ſilence, thy clients cauſe, thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours life, liuelyhood, or credit, or thine owne conſcience of truth, or peace of conſcience, for any benefit or Bribe whatſoeuer, though neuer
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:8100:58"/> ſo ſecretly tendred vnto thee. <hi>Turpe quid auſurus, te ſine teſte time;</hi> Feare thine owne ſelfe without another witneſſe, whenſoeuer thou art going about any wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> For without a ſharpe-ſighted witneſſe thou canſt neuer bee, as long as Gods Intelligencer and Spie, conſcience, is within thee, which ſeeth in the greateſt darkeneſſe, heareth the ſofteſt whiſperings, and <hi>Eliſha</hi>-like, knoweth what is<note place="margin">2. King. 6. 8.</note> contriued in the moſt priuate counſels of the Aramites.</p>
            <p>This ſaw well enough when <hi>Achan</hi> hid the<note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.</note> wedge of gold in the earth, Ioſh. 7. This looked <hi>Dauid</hi> in the face, and made him bluſh, when he<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> ſought to haue his vnlawfull pleaſure of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba.</hi> This beheld the Idolizing Elders of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,<note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 12.</note> Ezek. 8. when in their ſecret Oratories, offering incenſe to their Images, they bleſt themſelues with this baſe deluſion; Tuſh, God ſees vs not. This beholdeth the blood-ſucking Vſurer (in ſtead of lending, and looking for nothing againe, as Chriſt commandeth) eating<note place="margin">Luk. 5. 35. Deut. 23. 19.</note> out, and conſuming his needy Brother to the bare bones, which God forbiddeth, Exod. 22. 25. This looketh vpon the crafty Merchant, ſelling dayes, and moneths, and yeeres, at a higher rate then his wares, and if they bee too light or too deare, by falſe meaſures and oathes making amends for both, &amp; ſecretly checks him for making guile his gaine, and holding the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance<note place="margin">Mica. 6. 10.</note> of deceit in his hand, &amp; the treaſures of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity in his houſe, Mic. 6. and if he amend not,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:8100:58"/> will openly prooue it vpon him, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is gotten by craft and cruelty, <hi>the diuels Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimy</hi>) is as wild-fire in the purſe, and ſhall at length turne to <hi>Banqueruptiſme</hi> and beggery.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To be ſhort, conſcience, as a cloſe Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, is priuie to the ſecreteſt actions and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euery corrupt Iudge, which turneth<note place="margin">Amos 6. 12.</note> the fruit of righteouſneſſe into Wormewood, Amos 6. and by not preſſing iuſtice on the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, ſuffereth the iuſt to bee oppreſſed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice,<note place="margin">Ier. 5. 28.</note> Ier 5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Of euery corrupt Lawyer, who helpeth his Clyents cauſe, as the Woolfe did the ſheepe of his cough, by ſucking his blood, who by quirkes and deuices varniſheth falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and wrong, and iuſtifying the wicked for<note place="margin">Eſa. 5. 18.</note> a reward, taketh away the righteouſneſſe of the righteous from him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Of euery corrupt Iuror &amp; Queſtman, which in his quicke preiudiciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, reſolueth on the verdict, before the cauſe be opened, and euidences produced; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corrupt Witneſſe, who mocketh at Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Prou. 19. 28.</note> Prou. 19. And with the hired rake-hels of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> making no bones to ſweare and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, to the diſhonour of God, hurt of his neighbour, deluſion of the Iudge, and confuſion of his owne ſoule, beareth raſh and vnrighteous teſtimony in matters controuerſed.</p>
            <p>Thus the conſcience of theſe, and of euery of theſe, vieweth and knoweth what they doe, or intend to doe; and if it perceiue that they wittingly and wilfully doe tranſgreſſe, will not ſpare to tell them to their faces one by one, as
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:8100:59"/> 
               <hi>Nathan</hi> did <hi>Dauid, Thou art the man:</hi> Thou, thou<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> haſt ſowne the ſeed of iniquity, and thou ſhalt reape the crop of calamity: Thou haſt gone on<note place="margin">Prou. 22. 8.</note> in ſuch and ſuch vnholy and vnrighteous cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therefore canſt not but come vnder ſuch and ſuch heauie and grieuous curſes: Thou haſt willingly been led heere in the bands of ſinnes dominion; and therefore ſhalt, againſt thy will, hereafter be led captiue in the chaines<note place="margin">Iude, verſ. 6.</note> of Satans damnation.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, if it feele, finde and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, as it is nimble, ſenſible, and ſharp-ſighted enough, that your deſire and indeuour is to doe well; that you walke in iuſtice, and ſpeake righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous<note place="margin">Eſa. 33. 14.</note> things, and abſtaine from the gaine of guile and oppreſſion, neither making your hands the actors, nor your hearts the inuenters of any impiety; but ponder in your hearts, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with your tongues, and practiſe with your hands thoſe things which tend to Gods glory, and the publike good; then will it be benigne &amp; propitious, and no more rough and rigorous to you, but be vnto you as <hi>Ionathan</hi> was to <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 20.</note> a comforter in all your troubles, and in all your croſſes and loſſes, will ſpeake comfortably and cheerfully vnto you, as <hi>Elcanah</hi> to <hi>Hannah, Am</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>not I better to thee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many children,</hi> many Farmes, many fields, many friends? Why weepeſt thou? why is thine heart troubled?</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof well concocted, ſhould (me ſeemes) not only checke, choke and ſtrangle all ſinfull and vniuſt proiects and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8100:59"/> euen in their birth or cradle, but alſo mightily mooue and prouoke all Miniſters and Inſtruments of Iuſtice, yea all Chriſtians what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, to walke innocently with a perfect hart<note place="margin">Pſal. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> before the Lord, and in their ſeuerall eſtates and callings to giue all diligence and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, with our Apoſtle, to haue and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge alwayes a good conſcience towards God and men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Towards God and men.</hi> Which being the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude<note place="margin">Text.</note> and extent of a good conſcience, in reſpect of the obiects thereof, leades vs directly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any forced conſtruction, to this laſt, plaine, pregnant and profitable obſeruation: That, <hi>In the exerciſe of a good conſcience,</hi> there ought to<note place="margin">4. Part. Doct. 9.</note> bee a concurrence of our holy carriage towards God, and our vpright demeanor towards men. Requiſite it is (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome) vt reuerenter ſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>quis habeat ad diuina, &amp; laudabiliter conuerſetur cum hominibus:</hi> that euery good Chriſtian ſhould ſerue God reuerently with hearty deuotion,<note place="margin">Iam. 1. 27.</note> and man righteouſly with a ready mind, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall diſpoſition. Men are to bee regarded in<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 21.</note> the way of right and equity, <hi>propter famam.</hi> God is to be reuerenced in the way of Religion and<note place="margin">Rom. 15. 2.</note> piety, <hi>propter conſcientiam. Laetus lubenſque</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the ſeruice of both, that neither our holineſſe nor our righteouſneſſe proceed from a dull heauie feare, or any ſeruile affection; but that ſincerely without faining, and conſtantly without fainting, we be ſeruiceable to God and men in a religious and righteous conuerſation.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8100:60"/> Holineſſe and righteouſnes are the meane parts<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> of Gods Image in man, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, Epheſ. 4. Neither can we be aſſured that we are truly regenerate and haue a good conſcience, vnleſſe wee finde in our ſelues a meeting and marriage of them both. Remember then, O man, to ioyne both together, which God and a good conſcience will not haue to bee put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>Firſt, (becauſe God deſerueth firſt to bee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) be carefull to performe all diuine duties of holineſſe and piety towards God, according to the contents of the firſt Table; and then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, all humane duties of charity and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards men, according to the contents of the ſecond Table of the Decalogue, <hi>Suum cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</hi> But in the prime place, giue vnto God the<note place="margin">Math. 22. 21.</note> things which are Gods: and ſo for Gods ſake, giue vnto euery man his due: For the grace of<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 12.</note> ſaluation which hath appeared, teacheth vs, in reſpect of our great and gracious Maker and Maſter, to liue godly; in reſpect of our ſelues, to liue ſoberly; in reſpect of our neighbours, to liue iuſtly; to vſe our friends with fauour, our<note place="margin">Iſod.</note> enemies with patience; all, with beneuolence, and as many as we can, with beneficence, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Haec * tria praecipuè meditare aduerbia Pauli:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Piè. 2. Iuſtè. 3. Sobriè.</note> 
               <hi>Haec tria ſint vitae regula ſancta tuae.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>With the ouer-weening Phariſe, to haue all our godlineſſe in our Phylacteries, and fringes, and care-ſeruice, and frequenting the Lectures of the Law, no matter how we liue, is to ſeeme ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:8100:60"/> without righteouſneſſe. Againe, with the ſimple-ſeduced Sadduces, to liue indifferent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and quietly, but not to beleeue Angels or ſpirits, or looke for a reſurrection, is to appeare righteous, without holineſſe. Either of theſe come farre ſhort of that obedience which is approued and practiſed by an inlightened and ſanctified conſcience, which ſerueth not God by halues, in holineſſe onely, or righteouſneſſe onely, but in both; deſiring in all things to pleaſe God by an vniuerſall obedience, not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to any the leaſt liberty or allowance for the committing of any ſinne, or omitting of any duty, either of equity or amity towards men, or of truth and piety towards God.</p>
            <p>Indeed it moſt reſpecteth what it moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth, the obſeruation of the great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as Chriſt, the beſt diſtinguiſher, tearmeth<note place="margin">Math. 22. 38.</note> them, but yet neglecteth not the leaſt. It moſt of all ſtraines at groſſe ſinnes as Cammels, yet ſwalloweth not the leſſer as Gnats: It trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at wounds and blood, feares at faith and troth: It abhorres adultery and fornication, hates dallyance and rotten communication: It cryes out on bloody violence or vengeance, diſlikes all vnaduiſed anger, and dogged elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: It payeth the Tith-ſheafe carefully, and detaines not Mint or Annis-ſeed deceitfully; and albeit for peace ſake it will bee indulgent, and giue more liberty to others, yet it ſayes not to it ſelfe, An inch will breake no ſquare, A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle will doe no harme, or Small faults are to bee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:8100:61"/> winked at: For well it knoweth, that inſenſible decayes continued, prooue at length great brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſliding, leades to falling; ſlackneſſe, to defection; and as the leaſt cranny or hole vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopped,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> is ſufficient to ſinke a ſhip: ſo the leaſt ſinne cheriſhed and vncontrolled, to ſpill the ſoule.</p>
            <p>What faults in theſe our dayes more pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, then the remiſſeneſſe of a father to vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward children? or the carefulneſſe of a young man to hold his owne? or the forwardneſſe of a man of parts to purchaſe preferment? And yet we finde, that <hi>Eli</hi> ſmarted for the firſt; and our<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.</note> Sauiour touched the young man in the Goſpell<note place="margin">Mark. 10. 21. Act. 8. 23.</note> for the ſecond; and the very gall of <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> was broken for the third, Act. 8. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a good conſcience is, and will bee auerſe from them all, flying not onely ſcandalous ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, but the firſt bluſhes and appearance of euill, and hauing reſpect to all Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 6.</note> in ſubſtance and circumſtance, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no man in the wilful breach of any of them, ſeeme they to fleſh and blood neuer ſo ſmall. For the leaſt leauen of wickedneſſe, corrupteth<note place="margin">Iam. 2. 10.</note> the whole maſſe of goodneſſe; and the rich and precious oyntment of a good conſcience, is polluted and made impure, if but one dead fly,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.</note> one deadly ſinne be ſuffered, (I doe not ſay to light on it) but if with our will it lye, and dye, and putrifie in it. Auaunt then with <hi>Naamans</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rk. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> and <hi>Herods</hi> exception in this, with <hi>Anania's</hi> and <hi>Saphyra's</hi> reſeruation in that; with <hi>Agrippa's
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8100:61"/> modicum,</hi> and perſwaſion almoſt to be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,<note place="margin">Acts 26. 28.</note> (for this is but almoſt to bee ſaued.) Away with the glozing formality, and ſin-cloking po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of thoſe which make ſiluer Cawſeyes for ſinne, that they may goe thereupon thorow the world dry-ſhod, and ſteale away to hell with the leaſt noyſe of the world. Away with the mock-holineſſe and righteouſneſſe of thoſe ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious Statiſts, which make mans law the ſcantling of their religion, and better then that makes them, will not bee; further then that compels them, will not go, no not an inch, nor ſo far neither, but for feare, thinking all to be well, if the ſtatutes of <hi>Omri</hi> be obſerued. Away with<note place="margin">Mica. 6. 16.</note> theſe, and euery of theſe: for none of theſe can ſtand with the religion, price, praiſe and peace of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>It is but halfe a mans honeſty to be no better then the law of man makes him, which refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth but that (if all that) which the world ſees, out of the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger wherof a wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may liue. If he haue not a great man to his enemy, or but a great man to be his friend, (whoſe liuery as the world goes, is countenance enough to keepe drunkennes from the ſtockes, whoredome from the poſt, coozenage from the pillory, and theft too from the gallowes.) The law of man doth but looke to the outward facts, and pruneth (when it doth beſt) but the outrage of euill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but the rule and religion of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence looketh higher to God, and pierceth dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per euen to the inward man, examineth the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:8100:62"/> heart, reformeth bad opinions, and baſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and makes him in whom it beareth ſway, to be a law vnto himſelfe, beyond the reach of all humane lawes whatſoeuer, and ſo bindes him to ſerue the true God with a true heart, in a true manner; to ſerue God immediately in true holineſſe and integrity, without exception, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie or ſuperſtition, and men ſubordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Gods ſake, in righteouſneſſe, peace and amity, without fraud, oppreſſion, ſchiſme and contention.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to apply my ſelfe to the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<note place="margin">Application generall and particular.</note> of all in generall, and to ſpeake home to the conſciences of euery one in particular: Tell me, I pray', Art thou a man of ciuill faſhion, a reputed honeſt man, of faire comportment and condition, one that liueſt quietly with thy neighbours, giueſt almes cheerfully, in trading art at a word, in payments and promiſes keepeſt day and touch, in all thy dealings obſerueſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and truth, and payeſt euery man his due? It is well; why then, let God haue his due too, pay him the prime ſeruice of holineſſe, holines<note place="margin">Exod. 28. 36.</note> is his due; thou maiſt reade it in the forehead of the high Prieſt, Exod. 28. and heare it from<note place="margin">Eſa. 6. 3.</note> the mouth of the Seraphim thrice repeated, Eſa. 6. to teach what is chiefe in him, what ſhould be chiefe in vs, and whereunto chiefly we ought to direct our ſeruice. Pay then vnto him this due, and performe this duty of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Follow peace and holines, without which<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> thou canſt not ſee God, Heb. 12.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:8100:62"/>
            <p>Giue to him this holy ſeruice <hi>in ſecreto San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> in thy Cloſet, or bed-Chamber, in thy priuate deuotion alone, at any time of the day or night, as the good Spirit ſhall mooue thee; giue it to him eſpecially with thy family, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, ſpeake to him holily in Prayer, heare him reuerently in the Word, conferre with him religiouſly in Meditation, which is the life of hearing, the ſtrength of praying, the mother of practiſing. More eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, on his holy Sabbath, in his holy Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, at the receiuing of his holy Sacrament, when and where thy holineſſe ſhould bee at holieſt, come before him, and worſhip him<note place="margin">Pſal. 96. 9. 1. Theſ. 4. 1. Tim. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>cum decore ſancto,</hi> with an holy kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, or in the beauty of holineſſe, with godlineſſe and grauity, deuoutly honouring the publike Miniſtery, and in all, carrying thy ſelfe moſt reuerently, as Gods humble and holy ſeruant ſhould doe, and not in a ſtately ſurly kinde of holineſſe, or homely fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like familiarity, as many (turning their phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, into Phariſaicall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) haue done, and ſome yet at this day doe, and which is worſt, thinke, of right they muſt doe ſo, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Againe, on the other ſide, art thou a man which makeſt more then ordinary profeſſion of godlineſſe, frequenteſt diligently the outward exerciſes of Religion, heareſt Sermons and Lectures, readeſt Gods Booke much and oft, communicateſt with due and dutifull prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8100:63"/> and art zealous in refraining from open diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders on the Sabbath day, and in reſtraining thy family, and ſuch as depend and attend vpon thee, from making it a day of bodily labour, a day of riotous eating and drinking, a day of luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnlawfull gaming (too common euery where) that thou mayeſt conſecrate it, as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto the Lord, by both publike and priuate hearing and reading the Word, by conference, Prayer, and thankefull prayſing of God? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely thou doeſt well, and tis very like thou haſt a good conſcience towards God. But yet grow not heereupon preſumptuous; take not hence liberty, as ſome doe, to pay no debts, to put money to Vſury, to rent-racke thy Tenants, to deny the Magiſtrate his due of obedience and recompence, the Miniſter his due of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and maintenance, to be diſdainefull of thy brethren, couetous, reuengefull, and vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably cenſorious; as if righteouſneſſe, peace, and amity towards men, were not as well a part of Gods ſeruice, and a duty of good conſcience, as well as holineſſe and piety towards God. Yes, yes: He that doth a good piece of Iuſtice downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or tendreth his duty to his Superiour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and dealeth equally with his euen-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian neighbours, procuring things honeſt and<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 9. Rom. 12. 17.</note> of good report before them, and deſiring, as much as in him lieth, to haue peace with all men: Hee (I ſay) in ſo doing, doth not onely deale well with men, but doth God good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice alſo, and when he commeth from Church,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:8100:63"/> going about theſe things, may ſay truely; Hee goes to ſerue God: and this ſeruice of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, peace, and loue towards men, a good conſcience requireth and inioyneth, as well as the other of holineſſe, filiall feare, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip towards God: and ſo requireth and exacteth both in all, that it will not haue, either the one, to wit, Holineſſe, to be ſnuffing,<note place="margin">Mal. 1. 13.</note> puffing, ſhort-winded, and out of breath, as theirs was, Mal. 1. Or the other, to wit, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to be as a morning cloud, ſoone ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6. 4.</note> and diſſolued, as theirs was, Hoſ. 6. But both laſting and induring <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Alwayes,</hi> for all the dayes of our life, that in an holy kinde of righteouſneſſe, and a righteous kind of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we ſerue God from day to day, as long as there is a day left to ſerue him in; and that ſo we may bee pure and without offence vntill the Day of the Lord, filled with the fruits of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and Holineſſe, which are by Ieſus Chriſt, vnto the glory and praiſe of God, Phil. 1. 11.</p>
            <p>So then, to make a corollary of the premiſes, and a recollection of that which at diuers times before you hath beene deliuered, concerning the hauing and diſcharging of <hi>a good conſcience alwayes towards God and men;</hi> I will now, for your better inſtruction and edification, humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to your ſanctified memories obſeruation and imitation too, this Summary concluſion, as a liuely Character of a ſound conſcionable Chriſtian.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:8100:64"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A ſound conſcionable Chriſtian is he, who<note place="margin">The Character of a conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtian.</note> (hauing his conſcience inlightened by ſauing knowledge in Gods Word, and purged by faith in Chriſts Blood, from the guilt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, and from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing Lord) walketh cheerefully and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in the way of life, which God hath chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked foorth vnto him, not wiſhing it to bee wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or ſmoother, but going on therein vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely, neither ſtooping vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of a willing ſinne, nor fettered with the gieues of vniuſt ſcruples.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> He alwayes pondereth his paths, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his wayes aright, not regarding ſo much to be applauded of men, as to bee approoued of God; not looking ſo much to what hee might doe by his power, as what he ought to doe for his praiſe; being neither voluntary Agent, nor forced Inſtrument, in that which is vnlawfull to bee done, but holding all his ſences and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers within Couenants, for their good behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If his wiſedome and vertue aduance him to any place or office of command and authority, he glorieth not therein as in a Chaire of State, or Farme of commodity, but is glad thereof, onely as a meanes of furthering his reckoning, and pleaſuring his Countrey: wherein he wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthily demeaneth himſelfe, ſo che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and countenancing whereſoeuer hee comes and hath to doe, religious, ſober, and honeſt liuers, that hee dares not affoord a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:8100:64"/> good looke to naughty Varlets and notorious offenders.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Hee waigheth all matters, not according to the common beame of cuſtome and opinion, but at the golden Standard of Gods Sanctuary: Truth hee exerciſeth, as well in the cenſure of perſons, as iudgement of things, and will not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the wicked through bribery or flattery; neither condemne the righteous through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or enuy for a world. Being called therunto, he giueth plaine teſtimony to the truth, as well for ſmal as great, ſtranger as brother, and oweth ſo much to the Author of truth, that he will not paint potſheards, and ſay, Falſhood is truth, or truth falſhood; Good euil, or euill good, for any feare or fauour whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> According to his meanes and ability, he kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his houſe well, and therein is mercifull and bounteous; but his Church better, and therein is deuout and religious: hee looketh ſo to the Church, that the Common-wealth receiues no detriment; and ſo maintaines holineſſe and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the one, that he neglects not vpright dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and equity in the other: turne him what way ſoeuer you will, hee is euer the ſame, and will doe well: turne him to God, to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to company, to himſelfe alone, put him in office, out of office, turne him looſe to all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, references, and occurrences, hee holds his owne, and walkes honeſtly, honourably, warily, worthily, praiſe-worthily in all things, and wil not, to gaine any thing, though neuer ſo
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:8100:65"/> precious, leape ouer the pales, or goe out of the Paradiſe of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> In a word, all his dealings are ſquare and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the boord; in his promiſes and payments hee keepeth day and touch; his word is his parchment, his yea his oath, which he will not violate for any feare or loſſe; hee is a faithfull Clyent of truth and honeſty, and in the plaine way thereof goeth on confidently, and will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther triumph in his integrity, or ſuffer with it. To conclude, his ſoule is euery day dilated and inlarged to receiue God and goodneſſe; and is ſo taken vp with heauenly contemplation and contentments, that he lookes often as one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, on earthly pleaſures and preferments: he is very well prouided for both worlds, and is ſure of peace and comfort here, and of glory, and a glorious Kingdome hereafter.</p>
            <p>This, this is the ſound Chriſtian, which hath gotten the ineſtimable treaſure of an vpright conſcience; that true Diamond, which flings beames of ſolace vpon the ſoule. This is the conſcionable man, whoſe praiſe and reward is of God, though the diuell and world ſtorme and burſt for enuie. Such a one, be he Miniſter or Magiſtrate, be he Witneſſe, Iuror, Clerke or Aduocate whatſoeuer his place or calling be, (as <hi>Dauids</hi> ſouldiers ſaid of him) is worth a<note place="margin">2. Sam. 18. 3.</note> thouſand of the common ſort, who feare to haue a name to feare God, and to bee charged with ſincerity.</p>
            <p>Such a one (as you haue heard) the elect veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:8100:65"/> of grace, and lowd Clarion of the Goſpell, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was, and, according to my Text, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured ſtill to be. Oh then, that in vs the fire of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le for imitation of him, could ſo bee enkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d, that herein, and therein conſcionably comporting our ſelues in our ſeuerall vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we might, euery one for himſelfe, bee ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſay truly as well as he; <hi>Herein doe I inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour my ſelfe to haue alwayes an vpright conſcience towards God and men.</hi> Which that wee may all, (Fathers and Brethren) both ſay and doe, let vs humbly and heartily beſeech Amighty God of his abundant grace and mercy to grant, and for this end to giue to that which hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, ſuch a generall bleſſing, according to our particular neceſſities, that thereby ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences as are dead and dull, may be quickened; ſuch as are blind and erronious, may bee inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened; ſuch as are in a ſlumber, may bee awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened; ſuch as are tender, confirmed; ſuch as are heauie and penſiue, comforted; and all, ſome way or other, bettered, through the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull operation of his gracious Spirit, to the eternall praiſe of his glorious Name in Ieſus Chriſt, his onely Sonne, and our onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: to whom, with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, bee aſcribed all glory and honour, now, and for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
